<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cerevisiarii comes, or, The new and true art of brewing, illustrated by various examples in making beer, ale and other liquors, so that they may be most durable, brisk and fragrant and how they may be so ordered, as to yeild the greatest quantity of spirits in distillation : to which is added, the right way to refine and bottle beer and cyder, and a cure for those that are sick and ropy, so as to return them to their  internal sanity, as also the true method of manuring lands and the art of making salt water fresh : all proved by demonstration and sound philosophy, to be more agreeable to man's body than otherwise, and so not only fit for english constitutions, but also for transportation : published for the sake of verity, and therefore recommeded to all that esteem demonstrated truths before notional theory / by W.Y. Worth ...</title>
            <author>Y-Worth, W. (William)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13121</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11832403</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11832403</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67797)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 556:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cerevisiarii comes, or, The new and true art of brewing, illustrated by various examples in making beer, ale and other liquors, so that they may be most durable, brisk and fragrant and how they may be so ordered, as to yeild the greatest quantity of spirits in distillation : to which is added, the right way to refine and bottle beer and cyder, and a cure for those that are sick and ropy, so as to return them to their  internal sanity, as also the true method of manuring lands and the art of making salt water fresh : all proved by demonstration and sound philosophy, to be more agreeable to man's body than otherwise, and so not only fit for english constitutions, but also for transportation : published for the sake of verity, and therefore recommeded to all that esteem demonstrated truths before notional theory / by W.Y. Worth ...</title>
                  <author>Y-Worth, W. (William)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 121 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Taylor ... and S. Clement ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brewing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49723:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49723:1"/>
            <head>Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Work we here under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take is that of promoting profitable Truths in the World, beginning with the leaſt Eſſays, and perſiſting until we conclude in that, wherein the Happineſs of this Nation's Inhabitants chiefly conſiſts, <hi>ſc. Health, Riches,</hi> and <hi>Long Life;</hi> for be aſſured, That he who intends to come to the Top of the Ladder muſt not begin where he ſhould end; but firſt take the lower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Range, and ſo proceed gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally until he hath raiſed himſelf to the Pinacle of Fame, which is only ſet up for thoſe, that were Labourers in erecting the Temple of Truth, and
<pb facs="tcp:49723:2"/>not for ſuch, who never laid a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation Stone, nor indeed know any Ground to ſet their Building or Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der on; therefore from ſuch we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect any thing more than what their Airy Notions will lead them to, of which there be as many different ones as there are Conſtitutions, nay I had almoſt ſaid Faces: So that at this rate we might juſtly queſtion how we ſhould know Truth; ſeing that moſt Men have their different Opinions concerning the ſame, and ſo accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſtate their Doctrines; ſo that from the great multiplicity of Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it is very difficult to find the centre thereof.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing Demonſtration is that, which undeniably ſolves the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; we ſhall therefore recommend it as a ſure <hi>Baſis,</hi> for all the Judicious Inquirers to erect on; and in and among many profitable Arts, we ſhall give our Experience and Obſervation according to the ſame, concerning that of Brewing. For the right order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe things, which we take into our Bodies, whether Meats,
<pb facs="tcp:49723:2"/>Drinks or others, is that wherein the Health of Man in great part conſiſts; for if theſe are ſo prepared, as to remain in their nauſeous, auſtere Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityies, they ſoon Corrupt, Putrify and Mould, and being taken in, muſt by conſequence leave in the Bodies ſome Stains of the ſame, for being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly taken as Nouriſhment, they will ſoon demonſtrate their evil effects, by making a Craſy and Diſeaſy Body; but on the contrary theſe being ſo prepared, as to be in themſelves Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Brisk, and internally Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, muſt contribute of the Sane to thoſe that are thereby nouriſhed: Now Experience ſhews us, that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction</hi> and <hi>Fermentation</hi> is that which brings Maturity and Ripeneſs unto Beings; for Example, take any of the moſt Crude and Raw Fruits, yet are they ſo macerated by Decoction, as to be ſoon brought to a nouriſhing Quality; for the Wild and Crude <hi>Gaſs</hi> is by Decoction ſent off, and the generous Sulphurs the nearer Conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinated; ſo is it here in the Art of Brewing, for was not the Grain firſt
<pb facs="tcp:49723:3"/>moiſtened, heated and fermented, it would not admit of its Generous, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and Friendly Nature to come into the Liquors, neither could it be ſo fully obtained, but by the right Preparation, <hi>ſc.</hi> Decoction of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor or <hi>Menſtruum,</hi> which muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the ſame, that being the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to exaltation; in which Action the true Internal Tinctures are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: Now Tincture demonſtrates Maturity and Health, being endued with the moſt lively Vertues, as may be ſeen by that of the Blood; and it is from this, that the Oak, Cedar and Gold receive their Durability, as may be demonſtrated by their Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs ſeparated; but ſeeing this is largly ſhewn in our <hi>Spagyrick Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy aſſerted,</hi> we ſhall omit it here, and proceed to theſe following Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, whereby the Drift of our Intention may be the better conceived, and the Truth of our Doctrines confirmed.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the Action of the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Spirit,</hi> which is in perpetual Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Circulation, in order to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey
<pb facs="tcp:49723:3"/>Life unto Being: Now according to the Nature of the <hi>Matrix,</hi> and the Internal Decoction of the Form, the multiplicity of Natures do proceed, and by the various Inbibitions, which is a Decoction and Evaporation of the ſame, comes the various Degrees of Exaltation, without which there could be no Durability: Now that things may be ſo prepared, as to be made more apt to produce the greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, is plain by the Cuntry Man's Dunging and Manuring his Land, and the burning up of Stubble and Gauſe, by which the Crude Sulphurs are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and the Internal Saline Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues manifeſted, which greedily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit,</hi> being open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Nature the freelier to work therein; therefore is the Dunging the Land with Calx and Aſhes wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Philoſophical, and we know ſuch a way thereby, as to better the Land 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again we ſee, That Nature makes various Degrees of Concoction, by each of which the Nouriſhing Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are bettered: You have an
<pb facs="tcp:49723:4"/>Example of this in Man; for by the firſt Concoction the Food is made Chylc, by a higher one, Blood, and as it is inſpired with the Vital Flame ſo doth the pure and truly Sublime Spirits rarify themſelves for the Vital Nouriſhment, which indeed is the higheſt degree of Separation and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, whereby the ſeed is ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized and made the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of all, to remain in its proper Veſſels for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Generation: Therefore we will ſtate the Action of Concoction, as it naturally ſtands, to be threefold: By the Firſt things are made Pure; by the Second more Pure; and by the Third the Pureſt of all; therefore do we lay down Decoction and Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as the only Door to Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both in Nature and Art, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever unadviſed Men may ſay to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Again, another principal one is the Excellency, Fragrancy and Durability of theſe Liquors, which Nature ſo bountifully furniſhes us withal in thoſe Climates, where the Sun hath ſufficiency of Heat to exhilerate and
<pb facs="tcp:49723:4"/>warm the Fruits, and fully to extract from thence their ſuperfluous Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; their Durable, Saline and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneous Parts being radically unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Decoction, as is evident in that of <hi>Spaniſh Wine,</hi> ſeeing it admits of no Argel; and it is by theſe Degrees of Warmth in Decoction, that its ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and balſamick Nature pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, ſo as to make glad the Heart of Man. And furthermore we ſee, That few Vegetables or Minerals, without Decoction or Fuſion will give forth their preſtant Vigour or Form, by which their divided Parts are col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</p>
            <p>So then this only remains at this Time, That gentle Decoction no way deſtroys nor evaporates the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and Friendly Vertues, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exalts the ſame, even in the ripeſt Fruits, as is plainly to be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by New Wine or Beer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concentrated by Evaporation of its Moiſture, which by a due quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Liquor may be made into Beer or Wine again, as the famous <hi>Radol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus Glauber</hi> ſhews, which is confirmed
<pb facs="tcp:49723:5"/>by our daily Experience; and that Decoction adds Subſtantial Vertues to Beings, both in the <hi>Animal, Vegetable</hi> and <hi>Mineral</hi> Kingdoms, as by a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Examples we can at any Time demonſtrate, therefore now omitted, Brevity being here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned.</p>
            <p>We therefore from hence recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this <hi>True Art of Brewing,</hi> and the excellency of Liquors thereby prepared, really proceeding from De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction and Fermentation, by which they are rendred capable of Warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Strengthning and Nouriſhing our Bodies, and alſo of its durability too; for Experience ſhews us, That Beer ill brewed will not admit of Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for it ſoon takes a Ferment by the Sea, and ſo ſours and ropes: When on the contrary well brewed Beer may be tranſported to the <hi>Eaſt Indies;</hi> for having a Body and Ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs withal, the Ferment of the Sea exalts it ſo, that it becomes in the end like Mum in compariſon to the former, and will remain in its full Goodneſs many Years; and being
<pb facs="tcp:49723:5"/>Diſtilled, will give the moſt friendly Spirit, that can be by the Art of Man prepared; for its <hi>Eſſential Sulphur</hi> is radically united and exalted: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>(ye noble Engliſh Hearts)</hi> accept of Truth, though by the moſt deſpiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Inſtrument delivered, for this is that which ſhall ſtand us all moſt in ſtead in the Day of Tryal; for though the Winds beat and the Storms aſcend, yet ſhall its Foundation remain firm, as being built upon a ſure Rock; when as thoſe founded upon the Sands ſhall not be able to bear the Storm or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt; therefore that our Foundation may be rightly eſtabliſhed is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of him who recommends his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to your candid Acceptance, and himſelf to the Protection of Almighty God, who hath hitherto preſerv'd him in a Perverſe Generation from falling into the Pit of Error; which that you may all be preſerved from, is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of him, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſincere Friend, in all Chriſtian Love, W. Y. Worth.</signed>
               <dateline>From the <hi>Acca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demia Spagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica Nova.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:49723:6"/>
            <head>The General Contents of the Chapters of this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>IN which we treat of the Art in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, as alſo of the right way of Manuring Land, and the Sowing and Planting thereof, for the greateſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, even <hi>10. per cent.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>In which we treat of the right way of Brewing Beer and Alt in general, ſo as to make them the moſt Durable and Vertuous.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:49723:6"/>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>In which we treat concerning the way uſed in Brewing, in order for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>In which we treat of Fermentation, the ordering of the Veſſells, the manner of Tunning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſome neceſſary Rules, whereby the Beer may be long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>Wherein we treat of Clearing of Beer, and Reſtoring ſuch as is Sour and Decayed, ſo as to render it Drinkable.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>In which we treat of Making ſeveral Phyſical Drinks, together with their Vertues and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe; ſhewing the right way of Bottling Beer.</item>
               <label>POSTSCRIPT.</label>
               <item>Containing ſeveral <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning <hi>Thames</hi>-Water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:49723:7"/>
            <head>The particular Contents or Chief Heads of the Matter contained in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the Original of Brewing <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>From whence the Making of Malt had its Original <hi>2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The way of Dreſſing and Manuring Land for the greateſt encreaſe <hi>4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Cyder, Wine and other Liquors might become very plenty in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Beer being not well boyled ſoon Putriſies and Ropes <hi>13 and 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of Water as the Menſtruum of the World <hi>15</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:49723:7"/>
               <item>The crackling or ſighing of the Water is nothing elſe but the ſeparating the Wild Gaſs, which muſt be ſeparated before the Medicinal Vertues can be obtained <hi>16 and 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Right and Natural way of Preparing the Liquor or Menſtruum, ſo as to extract the full Vertue of the Grain <hi>18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Water, being Cold and Moiſt is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into a more Hot and moiſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by the Addition of Vegetables in Decoction <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Air rarifies and gives Spiritual Life to Beings <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Water is purged by Sand <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Water aſſumes to it ſelf the divers Mineral Taſts <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What thoſe Qualities are by which Waters are made more Salutiferous <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How that Diverſities of Water will cauſe Diverſity in Beer, made from one and the ſame Grain <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rules to know how far your Water will bear Decoction, ſo as to make good Beer <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The propereſt Time to take Water in for Brewing <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:49723:8"/>
               <item>The wild Gaſs in Water being not ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, is that which not only cauſes Beer to Corrupt, Rope and Sour, but alſo cauſes moſt Diſeaſes in the Body, even Sourvy, Gout and Stone, <hi>&amp;c. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſeaſes have their firſt Original in the Spirit <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Gaſs remains in Beer unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>costed <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tincture manifests Health, and cures many Diſeaſes <hi>35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That no Diſeaſe proceeds from well-boyl'd Beer <hi>36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Decoction and Fermentation is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Nature and Art <hi>39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Concentration of Beer for Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Extract of Malt is the Mummial Balſam thereof <hi>44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Gaſs is the <hi>Egyptian Dragon 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Salt Waters are made Freſh <hi>49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Nauceous Waters are made Good <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Author's way of Brewing <hi>52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to brew Double Beer and Ale, and their Excellency <hi>54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The way of Brewing for Diſtillation <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:49723:8"/>
               <item>What Quantities may be extracted from a Quarter of Malt <hi>61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A good Drink made from Molaſſes <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The beſt Mum from malted Wheat <hi>63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A good Drink made from Oats, Beans, Buck-wheat, or Liquor of Peech <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That Wormwood may well ſupply the place of Hops <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Signature of Herbs muſt be minded <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Author's Recommendation of Spagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Medicines for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Diſeaſed <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The various <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes of Signatures <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Preparation of the Quinteſſence of Malt, and its <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, for the bettering of Beer <hi>79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Office of Fermentation <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Seaſon of the Year muſt be minded for ſetting of Tuns in Fermentation <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Glauber</hi>'s <hi>Sal Mirabilis,</hi> or our <hi>Sal Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nariſtos</hi> makes an Artificial Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without Yeaſt <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The way to cleanſe the Veſſels, and ſweeten thoſe that are Fuſty <hi>90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The old Error concerning the Sap in Trees, corrected, by ſherring that it doth not return to the Root, nor congeal
<pb facs="tcp:49723:9"/>in the Tree as Sap, but is really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into the more eſſential Parts of the Tree <hi>93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of an <hi>Hppocrate</hi>'s Sleeve, or a Flannel Bag, in cleanſing Beer and Ale <hi>105</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The way to Clear and Refine Beer <hi>107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The way to make Sour Beer drinkable, and to give it durable Qualities <hi>109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to make ſeveral Phyſical Drinks <hi>111</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Phyſical Ale againſt the Scurvey, Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy and other Diſeaſes <hi>115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The beſt way of Bottling Beer and Ale <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations on the <hi>Thame's</hi>-Water <hi>117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some convenient Additions to Wormwood Drink <hi>128</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49723:9"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>John Taylor</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>MEdicina Practica:</hi> Or, Practical Phyſick: Shewing the Method of Curing the moſt Uſual Diſeaſes happening to <hi>Human Bodies.</hi> As all Sorts of Aches, Pains, Apoplexies, Agues, Bleeding, Fluxes, Gripings, Wind, Shortneſs of Breath, Diſeaſes of the Breſt and Lungs, Abortion, want of Appetite, Loſs of the Uſe of Limbs, Cholick, or Belly-ach, Apoſtems, Thruſhes, Quinſies, Deafneſs, Bubo's, Cachexia, Stone in the Reins, and Stone in the Bladder: With the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the Praecipiolum, or Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Medicine of <hi>Paracelſus.</hi> To which is added, The Philoſophick Works of <hi>Hermes Triſmegiſtus, Kalid Perſicus, Geber Arabs, Artefius Longae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus, Nicholas Flammel, Roger Bachon,</hi> and <hi>George Ripley;</hi> all tranſlated out of the beſt <hi>Latin</hi> Editions, into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and carefully Clauſed, or divided into Chapters and Sections, for the more Pleaſant Reading, and Eaſier Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:49723:10"/>of thoſe Authors. Together with a ſingular Comment upon the firſt Book of <hi>Hermes,</hi> the moſt Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Philoſophers: The whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated in three Books, by <hi>William Salmon,</hi> Profeſſor of Phyſick, living at the <hi>Blue Ball</hi> by the <hi>Ditchſide,</hi> near <hi>Holborn-Bridg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The French Gardiner, inſtructing how to Cultivate all ſorts of Herbs for the Garden; an accompliſh'd Piece: Tranſlated into Engliſh by <hi>J. Evelin,</hi> Fellow of the Royal Society.</p>
            <p>An Exact Journal of the Victories obtained by their Majeſties Forces in <hi>Ireland,</hi> under the Command of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Ginkle,</hi> to the Surrender of <hi>Limerick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s Works, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. 2. Final Cauſes. 3. Martyrdom of <hi>Theodora</hi> and <hi>Dydimus.</hi> 4. Chriſtian Virtuoſo. 5. <hi>Experimenta &amp; Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones Phyſicae,</hi> being a Collection of Natural and Phyſical Experiments; with a Collection of Strange Reports.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s Funernal Sermon; preached by the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum:</hi> As alſo his Elegy.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49723:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> In which we treat of the Art in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, as alſo of the right way of Manuring Land, and the Sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Planting thereof for its greateſt Improvement.</head>
            <p>IN this Chapter we ſhall treat of <hi>Art</hi> in general, and principally of the Office of Water, and Manuring of Land, together with the Definition of Brewing: Brewing, according to the beſt Senſe, may be underſtood to be <hi>The Art of making Liquors or Drink;</hi> and that by Decoction, which is properly to be underſtood Evaporation, not of the whole Subſtance, but only of the hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogeneous Particles, and a Concati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or linking together of the more
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49723:11"/>homogeneous ones, ſo as to make them the more generous and friendly to Human Nature.</p>
            <p>Now, as to the Invention of this Art, 'tis very Ancient, and hath a Phyſical Root, from the Word <hi>Coquo,</hi> to boyle, or to Infuſe or Digeſt <hi>Species</hi> in Water, thereby to extract their Vertues, and make them Medicinal; ſuch are the Decoctions generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: And we make no doubt, but that of making Beer was a Phyſical Invention, though not preſcribed, nor perhaps known to the Ancients, although one of late ſays, 'Tis not the ſmalleſt part of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it hath not the leaſt adherance to the Word <hi>[Chymiſtry]</hi> which had its Original from <hi>Alchymidus,</hi> a Jew, who had the Art of Tranſmutation, thence called <hi>Alchymy</hi> or <hi>Chymiſtry;</hi> what the Word ſignifies is plainly ſhewn in the Authority of Language, <hi>ſc, to be a diſſolving of Metals, and an extracting of their Quinteſſence:</hi> When as that of making Malt is only an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Fermentation, in order to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the <hi>Calidum innatum:</hi> And why
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49723:11"/>any ſhould ſay, That it had its firſt Invention in <hi>Egypt,</hi> I cannnot conceive, ſeeing the Art of making Beer hath not been of ſo long continuance, and that <hi>Baſilius,</hi> that famous Philoſopher, quotes it not from <hi>Egypt</hi> or <hi>Greece,</hi> but cites and deſcribes the making of Malt from <hi>England,</hi> as may be ſeen in his <hi>Triumphant Chariot of Antimony;</hi> and therefore <hi>England</hi> may doubtleſs have the Honour of being the firſt Authors of making Beer and Ale, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let her continue the ſame, in making the beſt, ſeeing <hi>Europe</hi> affords not better Grain, nor better Water to Brew, Decoct or Extract the Vertue withal. Now although the Art of Decoction is ancient, whence the Art of Brewing had its Original, yet do we not ſay that this is ſo too; but it is no matter whence it did proceed, or how old the Invention is, ſeeing it is ſo uſeful an one, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Drinks are made more generous, than they would by Nature be; the better the Grain is, and the more kindly the Malt is made, ſo as to be Malt indeed, the better will the Beer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49723:12"/>and Ale ſpend; and ſeeing all theſe are neceſſary to be touch'd at, we ſhall begin firſt with the Foundation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>ſc.</hi> the Manuring of Land, ſeeing it muſt be from Good Land that Good Grain muſt proceed, and conſequently the moſt Plentiful Crop.</p>
            <p>The way of Dreſſing and Manur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Land, which hitherto hath been uſed in <hi>England,</hi> is that of burning up the Stuble and Gauſe, breaking and mixing the Aſhes thereof with the Earth; as alſo a Fatting and Supply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Land with Horſe or Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dung, Fat Marle, Chalk, and more principally Lime; and of later Years, for Cold and Moiſt Ground, Soot is highly eſteemed and much uſed, and not without good Reaſon, ſeeing it contains a Nouriſhing Fatneſs: Now from theſe we ſhall make our Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, what that is in all or any of theſe, that Warms, Supplies and Nouriſhes the Earth with Food, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that, which is daily waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Multiplication and Vegetation; and though the Earth it ſelf, as it is a <hi>Paſſive Domicil</hi> or <hi>Matrix</hi> of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49723:12"/>doth not deminiſh one Grain either in Ponderoſity or Corpora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, as <hi>Helmont</hi> hath demonſtrated by calcin'd Earth, in which a young Tree was ſet, and after its being grown to a conſiderable height and Stature, the Earth ſtill remained the ſame in <hi>pondus</hi> as before; yet in all this it contains an <hi>Inviſible Spirit,</hi> which is exhauſted; and without a daily Supply, as well from Celeſtials as Terreſtrials, the <hi>Archeius,</hi> the red Man, the Servant of Nature, could not have any Matter to work on; neither could the Sperm be mixed or ſublimed to the <hi>Superficies</hi> of the Earth for the nouriſhing of Vegetable Growths; and therefore is not the Earth improperly called <hi>Magneſia,</hi> ſeeing it ſo greedily attracts the inviſible oily Life from Rains and Dews, and that joyning to the Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Earth, makes a great quantity of <hi>Salt Nitre</hi> by the Heat of the Sun, and the greater Quantity of <hi>Salt Niter</hi> there is in the Earth, by conſequence the greater quantity of Corn grows and increaſes, this, as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49723:13"/>
               <hi>Sandivogius</hi> ſays, is done daily: So that 'tis the fatter Saline and Sulphur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Qualities in the Earth that nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh all things; and, as we have ſaid in our <hi>Britannean Magazine</hi> of <hi>Wines,</hi> Lime by the Acid Juice of Vegetables, made as <hi>Glauber</hi> preſcribes, will produce great Quantityes of <hi>Niter;</hi> and therefore of wonderful and principal Service for manuring of Barren Lands; and dung of Cows and Horſes, by the ſeveral Retrograda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Nature, produces the ſame effect, for great quantityes of <hi>Niter</hi> are found where ſuch Fatneſs abounds; and therefore, I ſay, That Land may by Art be yet more enriched ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> for ſeeing Nature makes uſe of theſe, Art may in great ſufficiency ſupply her, by adding ſuch things as will increaſe the Central <hi>Sal Niter;</hi> which the Lime made from Muſcles, Cockles or other Sea-Shels abundantly doth; as alſo the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous Spirit of Stone-Cole, but more principally the Sulphurous Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the <hi>General Magneſia,</hi> which in plain Terms is <hi>Sand Drift</hi> diſtilled
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49723:13"/>and burn'd to Aſhes, and thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibed and moiſtened with the Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mial Life, which being mixed with the Ground will abundantly fertili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the ſame, not only to increaſe its Goodneſs ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> but alſo to cauſe decaying Growths to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new and vegetate afreſh; and this may be had in great Quantity, ſufficient to ſupply, ſeeing the Subject in <hi>England</hi> doth ſo plentifully abound: And that to the preſent bettering thereof, ſeeing Art prepares it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for Nature to work in, whenas things of a more inferior Order, as Lime, Dung, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt be waited on, till Nature hath prepared the nouriſhing Vertues that muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed there-from; for Calx is too dry, and by its great Heat will burn up many tender Growths, as may be ſeen, where 'tis uſed in Gardens, for it immediately burns up the very Root of the Flowers; but after it hath layn to mellow, and is fatted with the Sulphurons Quality, then doth it wonderfully cauſe increaſe, and better in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49723:14"/>ſecond or third Year than the firſt; and why then may not Art pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and imbibe theſe Calxes with a Sulphur, fit for Nature to work in, ſeeing this is all that ſhe doth by length of Time? Again, in Dung, that Rich and Profitable Soyl, in that it abounds with ſuch great Quantityes of Sulphurous and Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentous Fatneſs, yet the Urinous Spirits therein contained muſt be exhaled or drained away, or elſe 'twill prove as deſtructive to Young Growths as freſh Calx; for Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in my own Garden hath taught me, that Dung new made hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and cauſed ſeveral famous Flowers to die, periſh and decay, whenas that of Age hath cauſed them to increaſe in Largneſs and Beauty; therefore do they in <hi>Holland</hi> let their Dung rot, putrifie and corrupt, and throughly die, as being put in ſuch Places where the Urinous Spirits may freely run therefrom: And therefore ſeeing that it is the Sulphurous Saline and Balſamick Qualities, which only nouriſh; I adviſe, That ſuch may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49723:14"/>be ſearched after and uſed more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and eſpecially by ſuch as will be curious in the Improvement of their Lands; and if the Inhabitants will come to the Uſe of the Shells, then let them alſo uſe the Acid Juice of Vegetables therewith, or in place thereof Soot, gently dryed on a Kill, and they ſhall not fail of having that Increaſe, which will abundantly out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay their Coſt and Labour, for by the Variation of the Grain you may yearly expect a Crop. Alſo it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, That Orchards and Vinyards ſo ordered, as well as Fields, will not only bring forth the Kernel into a Shrub, but alſo yield the beſt Soyl for raiſing of Nurſeries, as alſo for dunging Orchards and Gardens; for though Earth, and Dung, and Fat Sandy Mold mixt together is good, yet not comparable to the Calx, prepared as preſcribed; and feeing that Land which is proper for Corn, Rie, Barley, Oats and Beans, is alſo moſt proper for Orchards. Why may we not improve that Waſt Land of Diviſions which are in Fields,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49723:15"/>wherein the Land-mark is ſet, and make the ſame of different Fruits, that ſo thoſe excellent Liquors of Cyder and Perry may as plentifully abound in <hi>England</hi> as Wines in many Foreign Parts, or Orange-trees in <hi>Italy.</hi> But here the Landlord may object and ſay, This will not only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Thieves, but alſo cauſe our Land to be trod and marred: But in anſwer to this we ſay, That the univerſality of Conſent in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Uſe thereof, would make Fruit ſo common, as not to be coveted with a thieviſh Eye. And again, a Law might be provided, as a Puniſhment for any Offence or Breach of this kind: Seeing it is ſo uſeful, that this may ſerve well as a Fence for the Corn againſt many a bitter Storm: And if the Trees are kept well pruned, and not to ſpread, their Dropings can be no ways detrimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to the Grain, ſeeing we have ſeen Examples of the like Nature in Foreign Parts: This may not ſeem unpracticable, though ſtrange to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but ſeeing Orchards, Vineyards,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49723:15"/>and their Improvements, are treated of in their proper Place, I ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it here, and at preſent leave every Man with that Opinion, which beſt pleaſes himſelf; ſeeing our whole Drift and Degſin is only and alone to promote that which the great and noble Hearts might ſo encourage, as to make <hi>Britain</hi> become the Glory of all the <hi>European</hi> Parts: Nay, I might have ſaid the Garden of the World for Plenty and Riches, being in it ſelf ſo healthful and well-tempered a Climate; but of this more at large in the other Volumes of our <hi>Hiſtoria nova de</hi> Britanniae <hi>Gloria interna &amp; The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauro Celato;</hi> now the Grains and Fruit being ſown and ripened, we ſhall come to touch at that, whereby Art advances the ſame to a more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Vigour: 'Tis ſaid in our <hi>Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean Magazine of Wines,</hi> That all Fruits muſt be gathered in dry Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, otherwiſe they'll ſoon grow muſty and rot. And again, all Fruits being taken from their Stems, are to lye on Heaps to ſweatand dry again, and ſo they become more ripe and fit
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49723:16"/>for the Preſs, and will yield abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly the more generous Liquors. And again, all Grain muſt receive an Internal Ferment by being malted or melted by a kindly wetting or yoting thereof, and then lying in Heaps to heat, and then flowered and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly turned; and 'tis obſervable, that the Fermentation muſt not be too violent, leſt it run to Beard and Husk, and after all it muſt be Killed and Dryed; in which Preparation all the ſuperfluous Moiſture is evaporated, and its Subſtance rendred durable; for otherwiſe 'twould be ſubject to corrupt and change: And ſeeing we have proceeded thus far, in prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and fitting the Grain, by a fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Motion, and the Action of Heat, why may not the ſame be as really neceſſary in Decocting and Brewing of Beer, Ale, and other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, ſeeing, that, as we have ſaid in the <hi>Preface,</hi> is ſo really neceſſary, in order to make them more generous and agreeable to Human Bodies.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49723:16"/>
            <p>But now, ſeeing by the aforeſaid Preparation, that the Grain is not only fitted and prepared for the giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth its nouriſhing Vertues, but alſo in great meaſure exalted, being ſeparated from thoſe crude, raw and Phlegmatick Spirits, which naturally adhere thereunto: Therefore is there is a Defect in Beer, Ale, or other Liquors, ſo that they putrifie, rope, ſour and ſtink, this proceeds not as a Defect from that of the Grain, ſo much as of the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> or Liquor, <hi>ſc.</hi> Water, by which the Vertues of the Grain or Malt are extracted, that being the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> of the World: But as it is an Element, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Waters, 'tis lyable and ſubject to the Curſe, as all other things be; and therefore hath Parts interwoven therewith, which have not affinity with the eſſential Purity thereof: For as the Philoſophers ſay, every thing carries its Life and Death about its own Neck: And if ſo, conſequently its Corruptions, which we can plainly demonſtrate in and by Univerſal Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that this Element is not Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49723:17"/>tute of, and much more in thoſe Places where the <hi>Central Archeius</hi> or Fire of Nature doth not warm and ſtir it up into Activity, by that living Spirit which rarifies and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the ſame, for by Motion things attract what is homogeneous to them, and are ſeparated from their hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneityes; wherefore Waters ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill ſoon ſtink and putrifie: Why then ſhould ſome of late fallaciouſly pretend to the contrary, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to make the World believe, That Decoction or Rarification is that which deſtroys and evaporates the living Spirituality of the Waters: No, that is not ſo volatile, but is that which gives Vertue, and muſt by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence be united with the Centre thereof, ſeeing Life always ſubſiſts in the Centre of every Body, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be touched any other way, ſo as to be exhauſted, but by Fermentation and a violent Seperation, which is an Exhalation of the Saline and Sulphur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Qualities thereof, which is that Earth, by which the ſaid Element is Elementated, which doth remain even
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49723:17"/>in Rain-water, after all the Moiſture is evaporated; and this is that in this Element, together with the Spiritual Life, which nouriſhes Beings, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Element it ſelt is only as a <hi>Menſtruum</hi> or Vehicle, for conveying of the ſame to the Centre of the Earth, where the Sperm is mixed and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed for Vegetation; and therefore if the volatile Aquacity is in part eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated, then by conſequence muſt the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> become more ſharp and powerful to act on Bodies; and as it is more ſatisfied by the radical Union of the Grain, ſo is that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, ſo produced, more durable, vertuous. and agreeable to Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions either temperately hot or cold, as will be ſhewn more at large in that Chapter that treats of Brewing: And although ſome, as I before cited, ignorant in the Law of Nature, do affirm, That Decoction ſeparates the volatile brisk and airy Life, drawing their Argument from the groaning, cracking or ſighing of the Water in Decoction; when alas this is nothing elſe but the crackling Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49723:18"/>or wild <hi>Blaſs,</hi> which is ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the firſt Action of Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and then ceaſeth, and the Water concentrates into Parts more agreeable: As for Example, take Water, and put it on the Fire, and make it immediately to boyle, and violently to evaporate in ſuch a way, that all the parts may be radically opened; and then imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately damp or put the Fire quite out, and this wild <hi>Gaſs</hi> ſhall only evaporate, and the Water become free and quiet in its Decoction, <hi>and is more powerful for the extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tinctures, as alſo for the making Eſſential Oyles,</hi> or indeed any uſe whatſoever; let others ſay what they will to the contrary; and the more eſpecially where the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs, that are to be extracted, are of an hot and generous Nature, as is plain in that of making Tea and Coffee, or the Infuſion of Sage and <hi>Saſſafraſs,</hi> and many others; in that 'tis a general Cuſtome to boy I their Waters twenty four hours, and only open the Pipe to let forth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49723:18"/>the wild <hi>Gaſs,</hi> which is purely Philoſophical. Obſerve, that this Experiment is beſt made in ſuch Veſſels, as have a blind Head, and proper beck only for Evaporation. And thus having in general run through what was promiſed in this Chapter, we ſhall conclude the ſame with this poſitive Affirmation, <hi>ſc.</hi> That Decoction and Fermentation are the two Pillars, on which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends Exaltation and Perfection.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> In which we treat of the right way of Brewing Beer and Ale in general, ſo as to make them the moſt Durable and Vertuous to Drink.</head>
            <p>THE right way of Brewing is by a true and natural Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> or Liquor,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49723:19"/>by which the Vertue is extracted from the Grain; which can be no other way but by Decoction; which muſt be ſo artificial, as to ſeparate the wild <hi>Gaſs;</hi> as was touched at in the laſt Chapter, That being the Grand and Fatal Enemy to Human Life, and there is no Element in Nature ſo much abounding with the ſame, as Water, as is plainly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in this, That Rain-Water takes into its Womb all and every <hi>Gaſs,</hi> that proceeds from other Elements; which is the reaſon that thoſe Places where Bogs abound, and the Air hath not Power to penetrate the Body thereof, ſo as to rarifie and enliven the ſame, are ſo unhealthful, and ſo often cauſe contagious Diſeaſes; for you muſt know the Motion, Decoction and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification is the Life and Exaltation of Beings, as hath been ſaid, as alſo the Purification thereof, in that they ſeparate heterogeneities, and conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate and ripen the homogeneous Qualities; and ſeeing theſe are of ſuch Univerſal Tendency in Nature, why may not they be the ſame in Art.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49723:19"/>
            <p>For Decoction is here really neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, for without the ſame it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to prepare our Food, ſo as to make it generous, agreable and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for our Bodies: For as that Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and profound Philoſopher <hi>Bernard Treviſan</hi> ſaith, in his Anſwer to <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Bononia,</hi> That Water, which is Cold and Moiſt, if it be well mixed with Vegetables, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes another Quality, and in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction takes to it, and puts on the Quality of the Thing, wherewith it is throughly mixed: And there can be no true Mixture of things of Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Textures, but by Decoction and Fermentation; but you are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That when I ſpeak of Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I mean not one ſo violent as to evaporate the Compound, but to ripen the ſame.</p>
            <p>So then, I ſhall come to explain what that Decoction is, which beſt agrees with our Mind, and is that, upon which the whole End and Scope of our Intention is built, <hi>ſc.</hi> a Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Wild and Unruly <hi>Gaſs,</hi> which is the grand Enemy and fatal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49723:20"/>Deſtroyer of the Life of Man, for reaſons before rendred; the manner how this is done, hath been alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready touches at; therefore in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your Liquor, in the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> let the ſame be carefully obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: For otherwiſe inſtead of having a wholeſom and generous Liquor, you have that, which is deſtructive to the fermentative juices in us, by its Stagna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing quality; and tho this hath been prevented by many in the Art of Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet it hath been by accident, the true Philoſophy thereof being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſidered: For when the Wiſe and Prudent of this Nation have by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience found their Beer ill Brewed, by making of them ill-diſpoſed, or by its ſoon ſouring or roping, they have ordered that the ſame ſhould be well boyled, and then they have found a better effect, by which boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſeparation of the <hi>Gaſs</hi> predict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hath been made, and this might have been much more eaſily done, and without a conſiderable diminution of the Liquor, had but the true reaſon been underſtood; <hi>ſc.</hi> by an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49723:20"/>ſudden, quick and violent boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then an immediate damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Fire, ſo that the <hi>Gaſs</hi> may evaporate; which will be more in one half hour, than by gentle ſimering in five or ſix hours; for the Body of the Water is radically opened, ſo as to let that freely paſs out; and then the Water attracts and receives in its place a vital and ſpiritual Life from the Air; for there is no ſuch thing as a <hi>Vacuum</hi> in Nature; for if Nature ſhould admit of this, Beings would ſoon be annihilated. But we ſe the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for Nature tends to the bettering of things, and aims at her End, rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in the ſame, as the Piſmire doth; and threfore is ſhe not one moment Idle, as <hi>Sandivogius</hi> truly ſays; but many times ſhe comes ſhort of her end, by meeting with obſtructions in the way; and therefore muſt it be the great buſineſs of Art, to help her where ſhe is deficient, <hi>ſc.</hi> by taking out of the way, that which is offenſive to her; And that you may yet the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conceive, why there ſhould be ſuch a <hi>Gaſs</hi> in Waters, we ſhall give
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49723:21"/>you the reaſon. You may remember, that I ſaid before 'twas the <hi>Menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> of the World, making one Globe together with the Earth, and having its centre in the heart of the Sea, and (as <hi>Sandivogius</hi> ſaith) hath one Axle-tree and Pole with the Earth, by which all Courſes and Fountains of Water iſſue forth, and diſperſe themſelves through the pores of the Earth, ſo according to more or leſs do Springs ariſe, and afterwards meeting together, encreaſe and come to be Rivers, and thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the place, whence they origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally came: Now as the Waters paſs through the pores of the Earth, and through narrow and ſtrait places, where Sand is, they leave their ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs there, and become freſh; ſo that 'tis a certain and Infallible <hi>Maxim</hi> in Philoſophy, <hi>That Water is purged by Sand;</hi> now afterward, as they paſs on further, they take into their Bodies more or leſs of the Nature of thoſe things which they paſſed through; and if they come through a place, which is hot and Sulphurous, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually burning, they are thereby
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49723:21"/>made hot, and thence Baths ariſe, for (as <hi>Sandivogius</hi> ſaith) there are in the bowels of the Earth places, in which Nature Delights and ſeparates a ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureous Mine, where by the Central Fire 'tis Kindled; the Waters runing through theſe burning places, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the nearneſs or remoteneſs, are more or leſs hot, and ſo break forth into the ſuperficies of the Earth, and retain the taſt of Sulphur, as all Broath doth of the Fleſh boyled in it: After the ſame manner it is, when Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſing through places, where are Minerals, as <hi>Copper, Allum,</hi> doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the ſavour of them: as alſo through all the other diverſity of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pors, that the Earth abounds withall; ſo there is no wonder why this Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be impregnated with a wild <hi>Gaſs</hi> as before-ſaid, ſeing it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes through ſuch diverſities thereof, in the Bowels of the Earth, and as it comes to the ſuperficies thereof in a more immediate degree, or as it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes further through ſuch places, where it is again purged, ſo doth it retain more or leſs of the aforeſaid <hi>Gaſs;</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49723:22"/>and this is that which cauſes the great diverſity of Waters; ſo that ſome are harſh and rough, others more mild, others more ſlippery and friendly to Nature, as ſuch which paſſed through <hi>Alkaliſated</hi> places, or where abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Chalk abounds: And 'tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable that ſome Waters ſhall waſh with half the quantity of Soap, as others will, which proceeds from the richneſs of their Abſterſive virtue and Salutiferous qualities in Nature; and from a Spirituous, Oleous, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Vapour, that they are impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted withal in the Bowels of the Earth, and where is that Philoſopher now born, that can demonſtrate to us, how much with this or the other quality Nature hath impregnated the ſame, ſeing ſhe works inviſibly, any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by the effect produced in the uſe thereof; or who dare preſume to aſſert that he will ſhew us the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act number of times, that Nature hath decocted or impregnated the ſaid Waters with different moiſt vapours; or how often it hath ſince its iſſuing forth received its purgation; or how
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49723:22"/>much it muſt be now decocted and purged, to make them equally gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; ſeing there is ſuch great diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of Waters, as is plainly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, ſome more friendly, others more auſtere, ſome more agreeable to one Texture, ſome to another; and tho it is ſtill but Water, yet doth it as much differ in ſome Caſes, as if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of different Textures, being ſo unlike to one another; for ſome waters are ſo prepared to our hands, that little or no boyling will make excellent Beer; others muſt have a conſiderable time of Decoction to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen them, or elſe they'l not be fit to make Beer of; we have an example of this by the Waters of <hi>Roterdam,</hi> of which indifferent Beer is made, as thoſe that have travelled can teſtifie: But a certain Engliſh Brewer, upon the well-boyling of his Liquor in the firſt place before Maſhing, even to a conſiderable conſumption, made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Beer and Ale thereof; which I, by my own experience, can teſtifie was little inferiour to that of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> which is highly eſteemed there.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49723:23"/>Here the Vertue of Decoction was manifeſted even by that Water which proceeds from one of the fineſt Rivers in <hi>Europe,</hi> for that it comes from the <hi>Rhine.</hi> The manifeſt Difference of Waters may alſo be diſcerned in moſt Counties of <hi>England:</hi> For, for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, let ſix Sacks of <hi>Hartfordſhire</hi> Malt, which was made from one Grain, at one and the ſame Time, from the Ceſtern to the Kill, be brewed in ſix different Places, or with ſix different Waters, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe Beers ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernably different in Taſt, although the Grain was one, yet doth this Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference iſſue forth by the diverſity of <hi>Menſtruums</hi> or Liquors: Therefore I would have all our Engliſh Gentry, Brewers, and other Houſe-keepers, that brew their own Beer, if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire their Health, not to hearken to Notional Theory, or to ſuch as are ſwelled up with the Poyſon thereof, like a Toad touched by a Spider, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to burſt without the Antidote of Plantine, but apply themſelves to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, the only ſole Miſtreſs of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49723:23"/>true Wiſdom; and in the firſt place let them, by many Tryals, prove the Nature of their Water, firſt by a more ſhort, and afterwards by a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Decoction: But in all be ſure that you ſeparate the Wild <hi>Gaſs,</hi> the Sword of Mankind; and when they obtain a Liquor moſt Generous and agreeable to their Conſtitutions, let them keep to the ſame; for in this Caſe every Man is properly his own Judge, and there is an Ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb in <hi>England, That every Man at Thirty Years of Age is either a Fool or a Phyſician;</hi> that is, he muſt then know what beſt agrees with him: Now for theſe alledged Reaſons, it is impoſſible for any Man to preſcribe an infallible Rule in Brewing, any more than thoſe general ones here by me performed; therefore I apply my ſelf to the Judicious, as my proper Judges, to determinate the Cauſe depending, and to Encourage and Receive Truth, according as it is delivered; God knows my Heart, I write not for Notions ſake, nor for Vain Glory, but for the ſake of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49723:24"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth and the Health and Proſperity of thoſe, the inhabitants of <hi>Britain,</hi> whom I ſo highly eſteem, as my daily Labours may eaſily demonſtrate, in that I cannot chuſe but caſt my Mite into her great Treaſuries of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But from the Digreſſion to the Matter in Hand; I ſay then, That all Waters are more generous that are moſt endued with a ſaluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous, Saline, oleous Life, and do daily receive a Rarification from the friendly <hi>Archeius</hi> of Nature; as alſo a freſh Influence from the Starry Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: But here, by the way, it muſt be obſerved, That Waters are beſt to be taken, when the Sun hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haled the damp and cold Fog there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from; and their Bowels are warmed with the benevolent Rays warmed with the benevolent Rays thereof, for to be ſure what Nature does not in this Caſe Art muſt; for this before-deſcribed <hi>Gaſs</hi> is not only evident in Water, but alſo in moſt other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creted Beings: You have an Example hereof in Wheat-Corn, which is the wholſomeſt Grain in <hi>Europe,</hi> and the Staff of Man's Life, in that it hath
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49723:24"/>received a permanent Maturation, both from the Celeſtial and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral Sun, for if it be eaten raw, or the Flower thereof, it cauſes Diſeaſes, but being fermented and baked the Heat ſends forth this ſaid <hi>Gaſs,</hi> as is evident, in that it becomes ſo Vertuous; the like is to be ſeen in Syder, yea, even in Wines, which are not to be ripened but by a Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, which is even a Spark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, foaming, or (as I may truly call it, Nature's) violent Decoction, even to an Exorbitancy; and all this is in order to ſeparate that, which doth not centrally agree therewith, <hi>ſc.</hi> the wild <hi>Gaſs,</hi> which is evident in this, That if a Barrel be then cloſed up, it will burſt in Pieces, for it will make its way out: But as ſoon as this is exhaled, then the Action of Fermentation ceaſes; but where it ceaſes before the ſaid <hi>Gaſs</hi> is fully ſent forth, there it cauſes the Liquors ſoon to Fret, Corrupt, Rope and Sour, as being diſeaſed in itſelf, wants an internal Sanity, and the beſt Cure in this Caſe is Racking it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49723:25"/>off. Now, it is obſervable, That what Decoction is wanting in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of this Gaſs, Fermentation doth compleat: And I wonder why this late Writer ſhould allow a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow in the Kill, to let the groſs Steams, ſullen Damps, and ſtupify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vapors (as he calls them) to paſs freely away, and to let in the Air, when he doth not at the ſame time allow the ſame Benefit to Water, which is the Element and Vehicle, which conveys the ſame to other compounded Beings, in the Act of Generation: And though Nature hath been never ſo bounteous in ripening the ſame, yet is it not fully ſeparated there-from: And Fire, which is in the higheſt degree Hot and Dry, that, even that, contains in it this wild moiſt <hi>Gaſs,</hi> as we can eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate before Men of all Qualities; now if what is here ſaid is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to demonſtrate the Nature and Effect of the ſaid <hi>Gaſs,</hi> then let ſuch as deſire to be better ſatisfied, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to other Volumes, as our <hi>Spagyrick Philoſophy Aſſerted,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49723:25"/>as alſo our <hi>Trifertes Saladini:</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, we ſhall add thus much, ſeeing this new Moddler attributes all the unhealthful Qualities to proceed from well-boyl'd Beer, and principally thoſe of the <hi>Scurvy, Stone</hi> and <hi>Gout;</hi> yet, we ſay on the contrary, That theſe rather proceed from Beer not well boyled, eſpecially where this <hi>Gaſs</hi> is not fully evaporated, for 'tis from this, and only this, that they proceed: For this <hi>Gaſs</hi> is Mineral and Excrementitious, and hath in it ſuch wrathful Qualities, as ſtagmatiſe the vital Functions, for it is endued with a Coagulative and Forming Quality, and will make Stones or Excrements, and ſometimes takes on the Bodily Form of Arſnick or Poiſon, it muſt be doing, although Evil. We read in <hi>Aventius Annel. Bavar. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Anno</hi> 1343. <hi>That above fifty Men, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cows, were turned into Stone. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telius</hi> tels the ſame Story, <hi>of whole Herds in</hi> Ruſſia. And <hi>Camerarius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, <hi>That in the Province of</hi> Chilo, <hi>in</hi> Armenia, <hi>at the blaſt of a South Wind (which happens four Times in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49723:26"/>the Year) whole Troops of Horſe have been turned into Statues of Stone, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Warlike Poſture as they were before:</hi> And <hi>Ovid</hi> deſcribes the <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Waters, <hi>which make all things Marble, and turn their Guts into Stones that take them inwardly.</hi> Which in plain Terms are no other than this <hi>Gaſs,</hi> which is plainly to be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinous Claſſes,</hi> though not ſo evidently in the <hi>Vinor</hi> one, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Calidum Innatum,</hi> or warmth of the enriching, drying Sulphur doth ſo dilate it, that it is eaſily ſpent in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction and Fermentation: But the Urinous and Mercurial Qualities do rather Increaſe and give Strength, becauſe the Vinor and Sulphurous Qualities, which are there, are ſo ſmall as not to be able to put into Motion, ſo as to work its way forth; now as the <hi>Vinor</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinous</hi> are the two general <hi>Claſſes</hi> of Nature, in that the very <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> which nouriſheth all things is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinous;</hi> ſo doth the <hi>Vinor</hi> contain the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinous,</hi> though inviſibly, as the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinous</hi> doth the <hi>Vinor</hi> in the ſame Nature, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49723:26"/>as the hot and moiſt, or cold and moiſt Qualities get predominancy; and from hence it is very evident, That this Spirit is the Original Cauſe of many Diſeaſes, and principally by its Volatility, for that Diſeaſes have their firſt Original in the Spirits; and that this doth remain in Beer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyl'd is evident in this Example-Take Waſh, prepared by the Diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, where neither Liquor nor Wort is boyled, but haſtened into a Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and being put into the Still, and ſuddenly made to boyl, as they do, the Beck of the Still being not immediately put into the Worm; till this <hi>Gaſs</hi> is inviſibly off; for if it ſhould, it would cauſe it violently to boyle over, and ſo foul the Worm, or elſe force off the Head of the Still, when as Beer well Boyled and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, having Age to boot, may be ſtilled without this Obſervation, and will yield by abundance the far more wholſom Spirit. The ſame is done in Syder, Wines and other Liquors, ſo ordered; and this is one Reaſon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49723:27"/>why <hi>French Brandy</hi> excels <hi>Engliſh Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Conſideration. which is a plain Proof that this <hi>Gaſs</hi> remains in Beer unboyled, is the Paleneſs of its Colour, which ſhews it rather to have the Moiſt Mercurial Quality pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant than the Sulphurous and Friendly one; Friendly, I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Tincture ſhews. Sulphur and Sanity, becauſe theſe are the Houſes of Light, and ſo chaſe away thouſands and legions of the dark diſeaſie <hi>Ideas;</hi> now Decoction only is that which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts Tincture, and by conſequence the Health-making Vertue: And I can compare white Beer to no other than <hi>Chyle</hi> or Poſſet, which is only made by the firſt Action of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, which, ſhould it remain ſo crude, by a debility in Nature, all Phyſicians would allow, to be the Author of many Diſeaſes; but when the Central Fire is ſtrong, to make a true Concoction, Digeſtion, Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Fermentation and Separation, then Tincture is brought unto it;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49723:27"/>which by the help of the Vital Flame is exalted; and ſo from thence the Animal Spirits elaborated, then doth this Tincture manifeſt it ſelf in the healthful Conſtitution, when Diſeaſes and Death are pale and wan. And what egregious Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe is this, even a Contradiction to the Laws of Nature, to make, as if that, which is her firſt Intention, ſhould be That, from whence Sanity ſhould proceed, and yet at the ſame time not to allow the degrees of Exaltation thereunto. Our new Moddler ſaith, <hi>That to make Malt with Judgment is no ſmall part of Chymiſtry:</hi> And if it ſhould be ſo as he ſaith, he muſt by conſequence allow me one Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein, which is purely Natural, and doth infallibly demonſtrate the Office of Decoction; which is, That Silver is made by Nature of the ſame Seed, and in the ſame Matrix as Gold is; but Nature hath ſooner done in Silver than in Gold, and ſo hath ſhe left it plae and wan; and from thence will proceed a Medicine but for very few Diſeaſes: But when Nature
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49723:28"/>hath by a through and longer Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction brought it to the Maturity of Gold; then doth it manifeſt a Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, even a Rich and permanent Sulphur, from whence may be made an <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> curing all Diſeaſes, ſo that this ſtill confirms, That Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture produces Sanity, which is the conjunct Property of Health: And this afore-cited Author's ſaying, <hi>ſc. That the firſt ſtep to the generating the Stone in the Bladder, Gout and Conſumptions, and other Diſeaſes, is the drinking of Strong, Hot, Sharp, Intoxieating, Stale Liquors, and Fiery prepared Drinks, as Beer high boyled with Hops,</hi> &amp;c. is a grand Miſtake, and really ſhews his Ignorance in true Philoſophy; for 'tis not the Uſe of theſe, that can cauſe one <hi>Diſeaſie Idea,</hi> but the Abuſe thereof; ſo as to cauſe <hi>Surfeits,</hi> or to over-power therewith the Natural Heat, and ſuffocate the ſame: And thus Food alſo performs the fame, and indeed ſo doth the beſt of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, when taken in ſo large a Doſe as to overpower the natural Strength; therefore let the Vertnes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49723:28"/>of things be obſerved from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Uſe, not the Abuſe thereof: For we ſee, this proceeds not from the well-boyling of the Beer, ſo much as from the wild <hi>Gaſs,</hi> when not well boyled; for we ſee no Men in <hi>England</hi> more healthy than the Country-Farmer, who keeps a Cup of good brown Ale and a Toaſt, and temperately will drink a Glaſs of Stout. For my part, no Man ſhall perſuade me, that any Liquors can be more wholeſome to the Engliſh Conſtitutions than thoſe of their own Climate, amongſt which good Beer is a principal one, eſpecially if it be but well and truly Brewed, Ferment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and kept in Age, according as it hath Strength to hold its Body, ſo that it is upon no Fret, but drinks Brisk, Sparkling with the Aireal Life and Richneſs of Spirit; then and then only doth it retain all the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues belonging to good Beer, even the Balſamick and Nouriſhing ones. And though thoſe that are troubled with the <hi>Stone</hi> or <hi>Gout</hi> may receive ſome effects of its Spiritual Action,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49723:29"/>in its being too Brisk and Active for their Weak, Craſy and Diſeaſy Body; yet doth not this manifeſt that it ſhould be the Author of this Diſeaſe any more than a good Medicine doth, which being taken by the Diſeaſed makes them for a Seaſon the worſe, their Natures being too weak for its healthful Qualities, for were it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would work the ſame effect on all, for what is centrally deſtructive will certainly be always manifeſting its Power, for that which nouriſhes, and hath Vertues ſo to do, cannot at the ſame time poyſon any other way than by that of a great Fire putting out a little one, and yet doth Fire and Fire agree: 'Tis true we allow it may give Pain, becauſe 'tis Active, Brisk and Spiritual, and will be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome good Office, as all pure Tinctures will; but it being deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the all-bounteous God for Food, why ſhould Men expect it generally to work the effect of a Medicine: But however ſometimes it may ſo fall out, that it will work a greater than many a Medicine will, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49723:29"/>eſpecially where Nature languiſheth after it, as ſhe doth where the uſe thereof is with-held: For we have ſeen in violent Burning <hi>Feavors,</hi> when all ſeeming Hopes of means have failed, that the Patient hath recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by being admitted to drink mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately of Beer; therefore in our Practice do we with-hold the Patient from nothing in Moderation.</p>
            <p>It being clear to us, that this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is miſtaken in the Original of Diſeaſes as much as in the Grounds of thoſe Arts, which he ſeems to kerp at, therefore in compaſſion to him, for his better Information, I adviſe him to look to our other Volumes, for the Original of Diſeaſes: And leaving him there, to conſider his Miſtakes, I ſhall come to lay down what remains to be treated of, for the Readers Information, in this Chapter, <hi>ſc.</hi> That Decoction is not only uſeful in the ripening and matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating of things, but alſo that there are many degrees thereof; for as that Learned <hi>Bernord Count Treviſan</hi> ſaith, for example ſake, in the Art of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49723:30"/>pure ſimple Fountain-Water, by boyling in the firſt Decoction, is joyned with the Fleſh of a Chicken, and thence in the firſt degree of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction we obtain a Broath, a good and perfect Decoction, the Humid, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Airy Parts of the Chicken being actually diſſolved in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Water, though there be other Elements therein alſo actually: But that it may be made a much more perfect Medicine, and more gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for reſtoring Man's ſick Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Chick is beat into a Maſh, with the ſaid Water already altered into a Boyl'd Broath, or with part of it, and is diſtilled by a ſtronger De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, whence a Broath and Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction will be made much more Noble and Generous, partaking of the whole Nature of the Chicken, becauſe by this ſecond Decoction not only the moiſt Parts, but the hot Parts, that is its Aireal and Fiery Parts, being melted into the Broath or Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are throughly mingled and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and therefore the whole
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49723:30"/>Vertue of the Chick is in ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction extracted into the aforeſaid Liquor.</p>
            <p>So then Decoction doth not only ripen and make generous but alſo exalt things to their full Perfection; and doth not in the leaſt deſtroy their Balſamick Vertue, as ſome ignorantly think, for that conſiſts in the Sulphur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Saline Qualities, for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial is twofold, Volatile and more Fixed; The Volatile conſiſts only in a Moiſt Vapour, interwoven with the aforeſaid <hi>Gaſs,</hi> by which 'tis yet made abundantly more Volatile, but the fixed is not eaſily to be touched by <hi>Menſtruums</hi> or any other ways, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'tis that of which the very Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Texture of Bodies doth conſiſt; and though the Sulphurs may be extracted, yet will the Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity remain abundantly more Groſs than before. This was pointed ſorth by the Famous and ever Worthly <hi>George Starkey,</hi> when he ſaid, That the Central Body of Mercury is a Peerleſs Creature, ſtooping to nought, nought indeed but the <hi>Grand <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49723:31"/>Tinging Light,</hi> which hath Power to tranſmute from a State of Corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption to that which is more permanent and laſting, or more eſpecially to that <hi>Grand Tincture</hi> and <hi>Divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> I mean the Magiſterial Blood of Chriſt, which is the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of Heaven and Earth, and the Fulneſs of all the Glories thereof; for that in him, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>dwells the fulneſs of the Godhead bodily,</hi> and in him doth the fulneſs of the Power of Tranſmutation conſiſt, in that in him one Grain of Faith, though no bigger than a Muſtard-Seed, is ſufficient to Tranſmute and Change the vileſt of Sinners into the beſt of Saints; and by him ſhall all things be regenerated and created anew, and redeemed to an Immortal State, old things ſhall be done away, and all things ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new, for do not the Scriptures ſay, <hi>That he will create a new Heaven and a new Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, as a Chriſtian, I am bound in Duty to believe him to be the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Panacea</hi> and Fulneſe of all; yet at the ſame Time, ſeeing by him that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49723:31"/>all things were created, we do allow that ſome Eſſential Vertue doth ſo remain in his created Works, as if concatinated will produce a <hi>Panacea,</hi> which by Mortals is not to be deſpiſed, ſeeing it emblematically tipifies the inexpreſſible Glory of the Almighty Creator; but of this more at large in our <hi>Ignis Aſtralis Adeptorum:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being omitted here, we ſhall come yet farther to conſider the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Decoction in this, that if it is gentle after the firſt wild <hi>Gaſs,</hi> nothing evaporates but the Cold and Flegmatick Nature, ſo that the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous and Saline is ripened; as is evident in this, if that you make a ſtrong Elixeration of Wort, you may by a very gentle Evaporation bring it to a Sap, very gumous, wherein the chief Vertue of the Malt conſiſts, for if it is done gently, you may at any time convert it into good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Beer again; which is evident not only by our own Experience, but alſo by that of the Famous <hi>Radolphus Glauber,</hi> where he ſhews, <hi>The Concentration of Beer and Wine,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49723:32"/>for the benefit of Tranſportation, and how the ſame, by the Addition of Liquor, may be reduced to its firſt State again, and of equal Goodneſs:</hi> And I ſay, That this Sulphurous Gummoſity is ſo manifeſt in the Elixeration of Malt, and all other things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, that even after a Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is ſuddenly forced, and after the Diſtillation of its Spirit it will remain in very large Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity in the Waſh, as may eaſily be demonſtrated in the Evaporation of the ſame, for there will remain a Gumous Extract, very ſweet and pleaſant to Taſt, of many excellent Vertues, being the Mummial Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of the Barley or Grain. 'Twas doubtleſs for this Reaſon that <hi>Glanber</hi> ſaid, <hi>The beſt part of the Malt was given to the Swine;</hi> for herein is contained the Saluteferous and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vertue: This being as the Body of the Chicken unto the Broath, and is not united with the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> or Liquor but by Decoction. Neither is it Volatilized, as is evident, but by a more long and ſecret Fermentation; and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49723:32"/>this is the reaſon why the <hi>Engliſh Spirits,</hi> as now made, are ſo unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the Body of Man, they wanting the moſt Friendly Vertues being filled up in Place thereof with the deſtructive <hi>Gaſs,</hi> the Liquor or Wort being not boyled, it muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main therein: For (as the thrice Noble <hi>Helmont</hi> ſaith) <hi>This Gaſs is not wanting even to common Water, all things being ſubject to the Curſe;</hi> and ſo curſed Liquors produce cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Effects: But what cares the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiller</hi> for that, he himſelf drinks little thereof, for he will go to a Glaſs of Sack, or a Diſh of French Brandy, and he ſeeks for Quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes and Profits from his Diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to maintain the ſame; this is the reaſon why we in <hi>our Art of waking Wines, Brandy,</hi> &amp;c. have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended well-brewed Beer, as the true <hi>Baſis</hi> on which the great Buſineſs of Diſtillation depends: And we ſay, That if the ſame be well fermented with our <hi>Sal Panariſtos,</hi> or ſome other Artificial Way, 'twill yield Quantity of Spirit ſufficient, conſidering the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49723:33"/>Qualityes that are ſo highly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced: 'tis not the great Quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Spirits proceeding from new Beer, which we eſteem ſo much as we do the Vertues of thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the Old. Let the new Moddler inſtance what he pleaſes, for 'tis generally agreed on by all the Ingenious, That Decoction and Fermentation ripen and exalt all things; and I make no Doubt but the learned <hi>Colledgiates</hi> will allow the ſame, why then ſhould not our Nobles, Gentry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be advertiſed in that, wherein not only their own Health conſiſts, but alſo that of the whole Inhabitants? For ſince ſo many new and ungrounded Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have been, and more eſpecially now of late, how many thouſands do there deplorably die away, yea even to the Amazement of Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: And I have but two things to place this on, <hi>ſc.</hi> The immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Hand of God's Judgment on the Nation for Sin, or the Inhabitants neglecting the Means of their own Health, by eating ſo much raw Fruits,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49723:33"/>rare Fleſh (ſo called) but rather raw, and drinking new and unboyled Beer, and poyſonous Arſenical Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, the very Bear, Lyon, Wolf, Tyger, Serpent, Dragon, nay the Baſilisk to Man's Health. We have an Hiſtory, That S. <hi>George killed the Dragon in</hi> Egypt, <hi>from whence came the Honours, Titles and Dignities to</hi> England <hi>and Engliſh Men,</hi> and will you now let the like Egyptian Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon inhabit your Houſes, and be harboured in your Boſome, when he deſigns nothing elſe but your Lives? Remember the Valour of your Ancients, and let him be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from your Land; let your wiſe Magicians conjure him into the Black Sea, his own Inhabitation; and let there be a Law made, upon Pain of Death, that none ſhall harbour his Eggs for Fear of a Cockatrice: Remember, I ſay, the good old way, and the Health and Innocency of your Fathers, who liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a good old Age, who perhaps never drank any thing elſe in their Lives but a Glaſs of well-brewed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49723:34"/>Beer or Ale, which proved to them more profitable than any of theſe New and Late Inventions, eſpecially ſuch as have no Ground in Truth; But what ſays <hi>Solomon? There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing new under the Sun;</hi> what are, have been, and will be again, ſo that New Truths are but the Reviving of the Old ones, or a Diſcovery of that which hath ever been, though not in general known; for thoſe that have known it have made a Secret thereof; and being Envious, and unwilling that their Fellow Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould ſtand in equal Knowledg with them, have reſerved the ſame, ſo that it hath died with them, as is evident in that of Staining of Glaſs, ſo as to bear the Fire, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron-Purple, and Tranſmutation of Metals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the great Diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of Mankind; for had it but been otherwiſe Gold might have been as plentiful as Droſs.</p>
            <p>Having thus run through the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory</hi> of the Uſefulneſs of Decoction and Fermentation, I ſhall now come to the Practice thereof in the mode of Brewing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49723:34"/>
            <p>But, by the way, I think it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to touch, how Waters may be in ſome Meaſure exalted to a more ſalutiferous and friendly Nature, which may be of great Uſe to the Inhabitants, eſpecially where good Rivers and friendly Springs are not. You may obſerve, that we before hinted at, the Nature of Waters, now how they may be graduated and made alike, is thus; Seeing thoſe are the beſt that go through Sand and Chalky Places, which do imbibe the Contrarietyes, as is plain in this of the late Invention of making Salt-Waters freſh; late I cannot ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly call it, being touched at by <hi>Helmont</hi> and other Philoſophers, but however it was of late that a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was obtained for the ſame: Salt-Water therefore is thus made Freſh, by a Precipitation or Imbib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Saline Qualityes by ſome contrary Ferment, and then the Aquacity may be diſtilled off, either in a Copper-Still, or ſuch Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as the Patentees have ordered
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49723:35"/>to sea: Now the matter proper for precipitating the Saline Quality is <hi>Salt of Tartar, Pot Aſhes, Lime made from good Chalk, or rather that of Oyſter, Muſcle or Cockle-Shels,</hi> or two or three of theſe mixed together, and made into Balls and thrown into the Still, and the Water di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled there-from ſhall be as purely Freſh as the beſt River or Fountain Water. Now the Philoſophy and Mechanical Reaſon hereof is this, The Alkaly deſtroyes the Sharp and Spiritual Points of the Acid, and fixes it ſo that that which is yet more Spiritual may aſcend: And the ſame thing may be performed by any other Alkaly. This is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why Lime, Chalk, Beech-Aſhes, Crabs-Eyes and Alkalized Nitre, or that of Coral, make ſour Beer ſweet, as the Spirit of Salt in few Drops immediately makes New Beer drink Stale.</p>
            <p>Why then may not our Springs be enriched, by cauſing them to run through ſuch things, as will make a Precipitation of the Saline,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49723:35"/>contrary Qualityes, whereby they may be made wholeſome, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to our Conſtitutions, ſeeing both Nature and Art daily perform the ſame; and Experience ſhews us, That it may be radically done: For Example, If you have a Spring, which is Saline, Vitriolick, Mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or Nauſeous, then dig as near as you can to the Head of the ſaid Spring, and round about it make a Bed of Beech or Wood-Aſhes, and then lay another of Sand, and then let the Foundation thereof be made with Chalk, and the Waters by paſſing through ſhall be made ſo Sweet and Pleaſant as to anſwer the End deſired. This may be done in any Place where the Waters aſcend, and where Chalk and the reſt may be had with little Coſt and Labour, but with great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the Drinkers thereof, ſeeing Diſeaſes (as hath been ſaid) do often proceed there-from.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:49723:36"/>
            <p>Now, your Waters being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, you may thus proceed to your Brewing: Firſt, make your Liquor or Water to boyle very ſuddenly, and when it boyles with the greateſt Violence, immediately damp or pull out your Fire, (as hath been ſaid) or immediately remove your Liquor into ſome proper Veſſel, there to remain, and cooll till the height of the Steam or Vapour is ſo gone as you can ſee your Face in it, and then put it into your Maſhing Tub to wet your Malt, as ſtiff as you can well row it up, and let it remain ſo about a quarter of an Hour, and then add another For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Liquor, and row it as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for if you ad your Liquor by degrees you ſhall the better ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Vertue from the Malt, then add your full Quantity of Liquor, according as y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> purpoſe to make your Beer or A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in Strength; then let the whole ſtand about two Hours, more or leſs, according to the ſtrength of your Wort or difference of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; then let it run into the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49723:36"/>and Maſh again for a ſecond Wort, but your Liquor muſt be ſomewhat cooler than for the firſt? and let it ſtand but half the Time; theſe two Worts being added toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you may put the Quantity of Hops you deſign thereto, and put it into your Copper, and let there be a large blind Head fitted to the ſame, lute all faſt, that nothing may eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, and gently boyl the ſpace of one or two Hours, and as the Goodneſs or Badneſs of your Liquor or <hi>Menſtruum</hi> is; remove then the Head, and let it out into the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer, and ſtrain the Hops there-from into your Coolers: And ſo have you a Wort, in which the full Vertue of the Grain and Hop is; which being cooled, fit for Barm; let it work, and then be tunned up, according to the Experience of the Brewer.</p>
            <p>Now, if you deſign it for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation, of ſmall Beer for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, then Maſh a third Time, with your Liquor almoſt cold, and let it ſtand not above three quarters
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49723:37"/>of an Hour; the which you may Hop and Boyl according to Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there being no Curioſity to be obſerved, the full and eſſential Parts of the Grain being before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, wherefore this is ſomething auſtere and harſh, but may be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated by a little Honey or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſes, and being boyled with Hops, Wormwood, or any other preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Herb, becomes excellent Drink.</p>
            <p>Now Double Ale or Beer is the two firſt Worts, uſed in the place of Liquor, to Maſh again on Freſh Malt, and then doth it only extract the Sweet, Friendly, Balſamick Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities there-from, its Hunger being partly ſatisfied before, wherby its Particles are rendered globical, ſo as to defend themſelves from Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, for being thus brewed it may be tranſported to the <hi>Indies,</hi> remaining in its full Goodneſs, nay rather enrich it ſelf; therefore muſt double-brewed Beer contain three times the vertue of the ſingle, becauſe of its durable Qualities and internal Sanity; whenas the ſingle, if not well
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49723:37"/>brewed eſpecially, ſoon Corrupts, Ropes and Sours. And thus you have in general my Sentiments concerning Brewing of Beer to Drink, of which we cannot, as before was ſaid, be more particular, ſeeing the great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Waters, and different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of each particular Brewer, which make conſiderable Alteration; and ſome are ſo practically expert that they need no Teacher, therefore our Intention here is no other than only to delineate and point forth the exact Method of ſeparating that <hi>Gaſs,</hi> which is ſo deſtructive to Human Kinds. <hi>&amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:49723:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> In which we Treat concerning the Way uſed in Brewing, in order for Diſtillation.</head>
            <p>THE way uſed by <hi>Diſtillers</hi> is that whereby they may obtain the greateſt Quantity of Spirit; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we do not approve of it, yet we think convenient to give it, becauſe they ſhall not think that we are ignorant thereof: Which is thus.</p>
            <p>Firſt, heat the Water a little above Blood-warm, that is, between Blood-warm and Scalding hot, and then the Malt being in a Maſh Tub, add ſo much Liquor to it as is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent juſt to wet it, and this is called <hi>Maſhing,</hi> then row or ſtir it up ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well with two or three Pair of Hands, for half an Hour together, ſtiffly, till it is all mixed in every
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49723:38"/>part, then add in what Quantity of Liquor you think fit, but the ſtiffer you maſh, the better it is, then ſtrow it it all over with a little freſh Malt, and let it ſtand an Hour and a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or thereabouts; then let it off into its Receivers, and maſh again with Freſh Liquor, and let it ſtand about an Hour, rowing it up as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid; ſo a third Time: But ſome will maſh a fourth Time, but then it muſt not ſtand above half an Hour, but I ſay that three times is ſufficient, the fourth being fitter for Small-Beer for poor People than for Diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without you uſe it in the ſtead of Liquor for other Maſhings on Freſh Malt. Now ſome very Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Perſons boyl their Liquor and coole in, which I well approve of.</p>
            <p>Now every Wort that comes is pumped up, out of the under Back into the Cooler, there to Cool, and then from the Cooler into the <hi>Waſh-Backs,</hi> and there let it remain till all the three Worts come together: And by the way obſerve, that you
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49723:39"/>neither Hop nor Boyl, as for Beer; now when they are down in the Backs, and in a proper coolneſs, and fit to be ſet, then add good Yeaſt enough to work it very well, as for Ale, and as the Yeaſt riſes up, beat it down again, and keep the ſame all in, and let it work three, four or five Days, according to the Seaſon of the Year, and according to the Temperament of your Back, when ſet, and Judgment of the Diſtiller, for a Back of Waſh, either too cold or hot ſet may be eaſily holpen, by adding in hot or cold Liquor; now if you exactly know the Time of the Waſhes being come, then you may take off your thick Yeaſt, to ſet other Backs with; but if not, then you muſt take with you theſe Signs, it will work it ſelf down flat, and then the thick Yeaſt will ſink to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, and what lies on the Top will be a kind of an hoary or yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Head: And you muſt obſerve, That your Waſh muſt neither be ſour nor ſweet, but in a <hi>Medium</hi> between both, for then it will
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49723:39"/>be moſt profitable for the Diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</p>
            <p>The way to work it into <hi>Low Wines</hi> and <hi>Proof-Spirits</hi> is as follows: Pump it out of your Waſh Back in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Still, until it is filled as high as the upper Nails, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about; and as it is pumped up, be ſure that another row all up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that ſo that in the Bottom may come into the Still, thick and thin together; let down your Head on the Still, but put not the Noſe thereof as yet into the Worm, but firſt make a very good Fire, ſo as to cauſe it to boyl, and ſo a great part of the <hi>Gaſs</hi> will go off, as much as poſſibly can without De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction; then as the Beck begins to drop, the Noſe muſt be put into the Worm, and all luted faſt with a Paſte made of Whiting and Rie-Flower: Now your Still being brought thus to work, if it ſhould run too faſt, with wet Coals or Aſhes immediately damp the Fire; and thus proceed to your firſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49723:40"/>to draw off your <hi>Low Wines:</hi> Now 'tis obſervable, That ſome Malt will in the beginning run off a Cann, two or three of <hi>Proof Spirits,</hi> and then it generally runs long; otherſome runs not at the beginning ſo fully Proof, yet will yield indifferently well: Thus your <hi>Low Wines</hi> being diſtilled, you let them lie ten or fourteen Days, to enrich themſelves, for <hi>Low Wines</hi> in that Time get by lying, but ſome think that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they loſe, but <hi>Proof Goods</hi> loſe by lying, except they lie warm: Having thus done you may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to a ſecond Extraction into <hi>Proof Goods,</hi> and then to a third called Rectification, which we ſhall omit here, becauſe (God willing) the next Impreſſion of our <hi>Britannean Magazine of Wines,</hi> I ſhall ſhew the Art ſo far, as that moſt excellent <hi>Stuff</hi> may be made.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49723:40"/>
               <head>Rules to know what Quantity may be Extracted from every Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Malt.</head>
               <p>YOU muſt, in the firſt Place make about fifty Gallons, or ſomething more than three Barrels of <hi>Waſh,</hi> and that in the firſt Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction will make 32, 34 or 36 Gallons of <hi>Low Wines,</hi> and thoſe, if you let them lye, will make in the ſecond Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction 11 or 12 Gallons of <hi>Proof Spirits,</hi> nay ſome Malt will make 13, eſpecially if in the ſecond Extraction you add ſome Water into the Still, and ſuch Malt will run two or three Cans, or ſeven or eight Gallons <hi>Proof Spirits,</hi> in a Tun, more than other Malt, nay ſometimes fifteen or twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. We generally count, That 20 or 22 Quarters of kindly Malt will give a Tun of good <hi>Proof Goods.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:49723:41"/>
               <head>The way of Brewing Good Drink from Molaſſes.</head>
               <p>PRepare your Liquor, as before for Beer directed, and when about blood-warm, add to every hundred of Molaſſes thirty ſix or forty Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons of Liquor, and ſtir them well together, until the whole is Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; and then up with it into your Copper, adding thereunto three Pounds of <hi>Lignum Vite,</hi> one Pound of dry <hi>Balm,</hi> and four Ounces of <hi>Nutmegs, Cloves</hi> and <hi>Cinamon</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; clap on its blind Head, and lute faſt, and digeſt twenty four Hours, then let it run out into its Receiver; and as it is fit to ſet to work, put your Yeaſt in, and let it work ſufficiently; then tun it up, and let it come by its Age Mellow and Brisk to drink, and you ſhall have an excellent Drink, very whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to Man's Body, and might be of great Service to thoſe Iſlands,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49723:41"/>where Sugar and Molaſſes ſo plenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abound: We have brewed Molaſſes our ſelves in <hi>Holland,</hi> and by taking off the fulſom Taſt, we have had excellent Ale, little infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to that of Barley: The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how Molaſſes are brewed for Diſtillation is ſhewn in our ſecond Part, <hi>ſc.</hi> the <hi>Britannean Magazine of Liquors,</hi> our Intent and Purpoſe here being only to treat of ſuch Liquors as may be brewed and prepared with the leaſt Difficulty.</p>
               <p>Now, it is obſervable, That <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wheat</hi> makes alſo an excellent Drink, and is very much uſed in <hi>Holland;</hi> but there is no Grain comparable to malted Wheat or Barley, both for good Beer, Ale and Mum, although <hi>Beans</hi> truly prepared afford a very good Beer and Mum, which in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> is uſually done. and Doubtleſs ſome of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Brewers know the Experiment of mixing the ſame with their Malt, a ſmall Proportion does not amiſs, but too great a Quantity gives it a Smack.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49723:42"/>
               <p>It is very good to know the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and nature of things; for though we may at preſent have plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all ſorts of Grain, yet a Time of Scarcity may come too ſoon, and then a Man, if fore-armed with Knowledge may in ſome meaſure help himſelf: It is good to fear the worſt, and then the beſt can do us no harm; let us not be therefore too much lifted up, for as there hath been a Time of Famine, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, ſo there may be again, which I truly Fear, and then if it ſhould be ſo, thoſe Beans and Oats, which now make the Horſe to prance, the Nation might be glad of for Bread and Beer; for as an Ingennious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon obſerves, <hi>The diſtilled Water of Oats doth ſo warm the Stomach, that it doth overcom the Senſes: 'Tis well known, That many do brew a very ſtrong and mighty Drink, with Malt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Oats, and how profitable the ſame might be to all</hi> Engliſh <hi>Brewers (if there might be ſufficient Store of them had) in a Dearth of Wheat and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, the ſame being rightly matched,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49723:42"/>or rather maſtered a little with the Hop, to alter their Tast, they can beſt-tell, that have made their private Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Profit of them, when others very inconſiderately have run on in their common nnd chargeable way of Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Liquor of <hi>Beech</hi> is likewiſe commended for the making an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and wholeſome Drink: There may alſo an excellent Drink be made from the Tops and Flowers of <hi>Heath,</hi> ſeaſonably gathered and dryed, and brewed as you have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for it. The Root <hi>Pottato</hi> being rightly ordered doth alſo make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Bread and Beer; why then may not the Engliſh Hearts be as well contented with theſe in Time of need, as they are in ſome of the Northern Parts, in Time of Plenty, with Stock-fiſh for Bread, as they who have been at <hi>Iſlands</hi> can tell you? Nay dryed Fiſh is eſteemed a very good Food in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:49723:43"/>
               <p>Now we having recommended ſuch Things to your Thoughts, as in the Scarcity of Malt or Barley make good Drink; we ſhall likewiſe touch at that, which may alſo help, when there is a Scarcity of Hops; the End of Hops being only to allay the exceeding Inſciouſneſs of the Malt by their Bitterneſs, whereby both uniting themſelves together, becomes a Savory and wholeſome Drink for Man's Body: Now this may be in every reſpect as well performed with <hi>Wormwood,</hi> and in ſome Senſe more agreeable, for <hi>Wormwood</hi> is endued with many virtuous Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; <hi>It Strengthens the Stomach, Reſiſts Putrefaction, Prevents Surfeits, Strenghening both the Retentive and Expulſive Faculty, and many more,</hi> as may be ſeen in every Herbal; when as to Hops we do not attribute one half the Vertues; 'tis true they purge the Belly of Choler: And thus appears the wholeſomeneſs of Beer above Ale, as <hi>Parkinſon</hi> ſaith; but however we are ſpeaking of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49723:43"/>their ſcarcity, when <hi>Wormwood</hi> is generally at all Times found in the Field or High-Ways. But here ſome may object, and ſay, That <hi>Wormwood</hi> will make Drink too bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: But in anſwer to this I ſay, That we muſt learn to know the Qualities of Things; for as we have ſaid in the <hi>Britannean Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine of Wines,</hi> one handful of <hi>Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> goes farther than three of other Herbs, nay than five of ſome ſort, eſpecially when it ſeeds, for therein conſiſts the moſt oleous Parts; and as the End is but only to mitigate the ſweetneſs of the Malt, therefore you may take ſuch a Proportion as will only mitigate, and yet not let the bitter Quality be predominant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with ſmall Quantities, and when, by ſeveral Tryals, you have hit the <hi>pondus,</hi> let that be your Guide in Brewing. It hath alſo been aſſerted in the Publick Preſs, That <hi>Centaury, Artichoke Leaves,</hi> or <hi>Aloes Hepatique,</hi> as having a Signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the Hop, may, if right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed, ſupply the ſcarcity thereof;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49723:44"/>but you muſt learn by Experience to acquaint your ſelf with the Knowledge of the internal Quality of things, there being ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Difference in things of the ſame kind or <hi>ſpecies:</hi> You have an Example of this in <hi>Arſmart,</hi> for the Male is twice as ſtrong as that of the Female; and yet they are both ſtill <hi>Arſmart;</hi> therefore I ſay, That the Signature muſt be learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and known where the full Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is ſtamped: It is true this Defect cannot wholly be attributed to generous Nature; becauſe ſhe is alwayes ready to work is Sperm, as God doth in the Free-will of Man, as <hi>Sandivogius</hi> truly ſaith, The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is in the Matrix or Place, as being either over-burthened with the predicted <hi>Gaſs,</hi> or elſe with ſtinking ſulphurous Excrements: So that if Vegetation from thence proceeds of this, that or the other kind, the Vegetable or Mineral ſo produced is not by half ſo Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, nay in ſome degree 'tis quite oppoſite to that, which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49723:44"/>from a good Soyl: But how little do the Phyſicians or Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this Land conſider this? for, ſay they, ſure of Vegetables of this, or that, or th'other Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, either Temperately Dry, Hot, Cold or Moiſt, did perform this, that, or th'other Cure, on this or that Conſtitution, with which it ſympathized, it muſt do it again; but yet for all this, when they have preſcribed them, they have found themſelves much deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not conceiving the Reaſon thereof, they have aſcribed it to ſome more hidden Cauſe, when alas the Reaſon is obvious. It is alſo evident that one Field doth not bring forth Grain in all things exactly alike with the other; neither doth one Soyl continue to produce the ſame effect for Years together, for the Crops in Time of Harveſt will be conſiderably different, one Good, Full and Pleaſantly nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing, the other Dwindling and Hungry: Therefore is it requiſite,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49723:45"/>as the Countryman yearly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, to alter the Grain; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this Caſe there might be a conſiderable Remedy, were but the Land equally manured yearly; for it is but a ſupplying of the radical Moiſture, Salt Nitral Vertue, or Oleous Milk, equal to the Strength of the Grain ſowed therein, which every diſtinct Concreate ſucks forth in its Vegetation: For it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in the whole Courſe of Nature, that every thing requires a continual Supply; otherwiſe, that being thereof deprived, would ſoon be exhauſted, as we have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſaid. The Preſidents we have of this Nature are endleſs to be reckoned up; but ſeeing there is a Cloud of Witneſſes, we ſhall omit it, and only recommend to thoſe, that are not ſatisfied in this Point, the adjournal of their day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deſire to Food, without which it would be impoſſible to ſubſiſt: And ſeeing things are ſo evidently different, although they proceed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49723:45"/>from Land well manured, what muſt thoſe then be, that proceed from Land never manured at all; therefore it is not ſufficient that it is <hi>Arſmart,</hi> but its ſufficiency lies in this, <hi>ſc.</hi> in having the true Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature thereon: Nay, more than this, even to the Superlative De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that you gather it, when the Signature is in its full Reign and Dominion, ſiting (as I may ſay) in the Throne of that Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and contributing Vertue to all its Parts; for if you know not this, you may certainly miſs of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame in its preſtant Vigour, for we mind not ſo much the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitary Hours, as we do the Signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Things, this being ſo really neceſſary to qualifie a Phyſician; therefore I wonder what the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary</hi> thinks, when he employs Old Women to gather his Simples, who do it at all Times, and in all Places, where they can find moſt; they (poor Hearts) know no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is a Livelihood that they want, and the <hi>Apothecary</hi> buys it
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49723:46"/>cheap, to make up his <hi>Hodg-podge of all together,</hi> which is a main Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, That (as the worthy <hi>Robert Boyle</hi> ſaid) <hi>ſo many Diſeaſes are Cured in Books, and ſo few in Beds;</hi> we therefore cannot chuſe but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to the Inhabitants of this Nation <hi>Spagyrical Medicines;</hi> ſuch we mean as are prepared by ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the Good from the Bad, that is, the friendly Balſamick Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only from the Corruptions, which hinder its free Action, which can never be obtained by any of the Violent Fires of the <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> the which we do utterly deteſt; but by the Knowledge of the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> in her Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power, but of this more at large in our ſeveral Volumes of the <hi>New Hiſtory of</hi> Britain<hi>'s Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory and Hidden Treaſure:</hi> But here to the matter in hand; and we ſay, That it is not only <hi>Arſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mart,</hi> which hath this Difference, but alſo <hi>Wormwood, Mugwort, Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Scarlea, Vervine,</hi> nay even <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> and <hi>Rhubarbe, Scammony,</hi> and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49723:46"/>almoſt all other Simples; therefore are the Rules here predicted neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be conſidered, by every In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Perſon, that ſo they may in this Caſe help themſelves. Now having touched at Signatures in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, we think it convenient to give a Touch at thoſe that are Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneous, and ſtand neareſt in Affinity each to other, as <hi>Wheat-Corn</hi> doth to that of the <hi>Vine</hi> in general; but the <hi>Vine</hi> hath ſeveral Variations of Signatures, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the different Sorts of Wines, both in <hi>Spain, Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Sherry, Canary, Malago, Rhemiſh, White Wine, Claret, Rappadavia;</hi> alſo <hi>Champaign, Burgundy, Frontineack, Greek</hi> or <hi>Florence Wines,</hi> &amp;c. Now the Herb <hi>Scarlea</hi> hath a Signature agreeing with that of the <hi>Muſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine Grape;</hi> the Herb <hi>Clary</hi> with the <hi>Rheniſh;</hi> the <hi>White Currant Tree</hi> with the <hi>White;</hi> and the <hi>Bramble</hi> with the <hi>Red,</hi> therefore doth its Fruit, being rightly mixed with good Pippen or Pearmain-Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, make good Claret: We could
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49723:47"/>cite more of the like nature, but we deſign to treat more largly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the next Impreſſion of our <hi>Britannean Magazine of Wines,</hi> and our Intent here is not to fill theſe Sheets with <hi>Theory,</hi> but to point forth that, which may redound to conſiderable Advantage in <hi>Practice,</hi> though indeed amongſt others, the right Knowledge of Signatures, and how they are ſuperiour in Quality or more agreeing is not the leaſt: For, for Example, although <hi>Clary</hi> hath a Signature with the <hi>Rheniſh-Grape,</hi> yet is its Quality of a more ſuperior degree, for its Eſſence is more concatinated than that of the <hi>Vine,</hi> for a few Leaves thereof will reliſh other Juices with as much Taſte as a whole Hogſhed of the Vine's own Juice, as is manifeſtly known to all <hi>Wine-Brewers</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillers;</hi> and therefore if you Deſign to make good Beer, or Artificial Wines, pleaſant to taſt, like the Natural, you muſt not over-doſe the predominant Signature; for then you give it an unſavory one; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49723:47"/>where we have preſcribed, in the Chapter of <hi>Artificial Wines,</hi> in the <hi>Britannean Magazine,</hi> the Juice or Water of <hi>Clary,</hi> one part to half or equal Parts of that of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Texture, there we mean the Juice or Water ſo artificially pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, as not to exceed the Taſt of that, which naturally proceeds from the Vine; this is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in all Liquors whatever. And again, <hi>Brandy,</hi> as it is generally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled from ſmall Wines, Lees, ſometimes pricked Wines, or thoſe going to decay, variouſly mixed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſo fermented with Stum, or ſome other artificial way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſtilled, the Spirits come up friendly, and with a pleaſant <hi>Hogo,</hi> and Balſamick Taſt, for the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Flavours are ſo mixed as to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate each other, for the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon given for Malt and Hops; for many of them are ſouriſh before Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled, and thoſe moderate the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding luſceouſneſs of others.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:49723:48"/>
               <p>Now our <hi>Diſtillers</hi> and <hi>Artificial Rectifiers</hi> have various Phantaſies in the Imitation of the Flavours of <hi>Brandy,</hi> by rectifying from <hi>Bay Salt, Bay Leaves;</hi> others from <hi>Orrice, Ginger. Arſmart, Pepper-Wort, Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Clary,</hi> and many others, there being hardly a <hi>Diſtiller</hi> but hath a different way to that of another: yet the exact Flavors to <hi>Artificial Brandy</hi> are wanting in this Land: there being three things abſolutely neceſſary before you can in any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree come near it; that is, To bereave it of Mr. <hi>Hogo</hi> or the ill Tangue, and then to introduce the Tart and Rasberry Taſt, intermix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but here you muſt have a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whoſe Textures is proper to work on, for though we are able to perform much in this Caſe, nay more than what we have hitherto ſeen, and have mentioned the ſame in our <hi>Britannean Magazine of Wines,</hi> yet let us be rightly underſtood; For that thoſe Spirits generally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from Malt, have two Grand
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49723:48"/>Defects, the one is, 'tis filled with the Wild <hi>Gaſs,</hi> whence that <hi>Hogo</hi> or ill Tangue in great Meaſure proceeds. The other is, it wants that Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam or Extract, which is in the <hi>Waſh,</hi> and is given to the Swine, to be dilated by a due Decoction and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation into the Body thereof, and then hath it ſomething more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial to work on, and therefore have we mentioned, and laid our Ground upon well-brewed Beer, and then that Diſtilled and Rectified, to as to be as free from Taſt as Water, only Fiery and Spirituous; and thou may you thereinto introduce ſome Friendly Flavours, which may be as agreeable to Engliſh Conſtitutions, nay more than that of <hi>France,</hi> becauſe of its being produced from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Soyl and Climatory affinity: Now in this Caſe to make <hi>Artificial Brandy,</hi> we lay a greater Streſs upon Cyder and Perry, for that, as we ſay there, excellent Spirits may be thence produced for the making <hi>Artificial Brandy;</hi> alſo from <hi>Artificial Wines,</hi> and eſpecially thoſe that are brought
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49723:49"/>to the Taſt of the Natural ones: much may alſo be performed on <hi>fine Goods, ſc.</hi> the Spirit of Molaſſes, and eſpecially if you know the Nature, Preparation and Office of <hi>Glauber</hi>'s <hi>Sal Mirabilis, Paracelſus</hi>'s <hi>Sal Enixum</hi> or our <hi>Sal Panariſtos,</hi> which we have alſo there touched at, in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter treating of <hi>Artificial Brandy,</hi> the which we ſhall hereafter more fully explain.</p>
               <p>Thus we have intimated to you, how you may fit your Signatures ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Predominancy of the Quality of that you joyn it unto, by adding ſmaller or larger Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and have not only touched at the Manuring of Land, ſhewing by what 'tis bettered, but alſo ſhewing the Nature of Waters, and the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Wild <hi>Gaſs,</hi> and how Salt Waters are made Freſh, together with the making of Waters more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious for the uſe of Families, as alſo the two different ways of Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo that you may chuſe which you will, as alſo having touched at things commodious thereunto; we
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49723:49"/>ſhall now come to ſpeak of the <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence</hi> of <hi>Malt,</hi> becauſe therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts many Myſteries, not only for the Nouriſhment of Human Kinds, but alſo for the reſtoring of Sick, Ropy, Sour and Decayed Beer to an Internal Sanity.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of <hi>Malt</hi> is the Vertue or pureſt Subſtance thereof, extracted and ſeperated from all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities; and therefore muſt it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Vertue of the whole, and be very beneficial, as is ſaid, for the uſe predicted; therefore I wiſh the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration thereof were better known, for the which, that we may in ſome meaſure contribute our Mite, we ſhall inſtance the ſame as follows; there is one way which is the more excellent, which is, <hi>to diſſolve the whole Body by the Volatile Spirit of our</hi> Sal Panariſtos, <hi>and then the</hi> Menſtruum <hi>wholy ſeperated therefrom, and ſo have you the Quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or whole Vertue of the Malt entire;</hi> which will at any Time contribute Sanity to its own diſeaſed <hi>Species,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly applyed.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:49723:50"/>
               <p>Another way is, <hi>The Extracting of a good</hi> Aqua Vitae <hi>from well-brewed Beer, and then the Gumous and Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick Subſtance from Good Sound Malt, and theſe united through the</hi> Medium of Nature, <hi>and ſo preſerved for uſe;</hi> for as an Ingenious Perſon obſerves, A ſmall Doſe of this preſerves, and is far more excellent than abundance of that, wherein the Flegmatick Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial Vapour or Evil Sulphurous Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or Saline Aſtringent one is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant, for here the pure Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are exalted, and brought to an homogenious Aſſinity, and ſo ſtand as a <hi>Medium</hi> to oppoſe any contrary Quality that ſtrives for Predominancy in the Liquors or Juices that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared from that Subject, whoſe Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence this is; therefore have we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended that of Wines, in our <hi>Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean Magazinc of Liquors,</hi> for the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch as are Sick, Ropy and Diſſeaſed, as we do this here for Beer. We may alſo commend the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of <hi>Metals</hi> for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of Metals; as alſo the <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> for the preſerving
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49723:50"/>his Health, which is the Spirit of the Blood and Bones united with the Mummial Balſam, the beſt whereof is that from the Deſerts of <hi>Arabia</hi> (which every <hi>Druggiſt</hi> perhaps will tell you he hath) but be ſure you have the right, if you expect to make the true <hi>Quinteſſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>Quinteſſences</hi> are as much ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior in Medicinal Vertues to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects whence extracted, as the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Celeſtial Orbs are to the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior and Terreſtrial ones; but ſeeing we have more largely treated thereof in our <hi>Ignis Aſtralis Adeptorum,</hi> we ſhall omit it here, and ſo conclude this Chapter.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:49723:51"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> In which we treat of Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Ordering the Veſſels, the manner of Tunning, and ſome Neceſſary Rules, whereby the Beer may be long preſerved.</head>
            <p>AS to the Doctrine of Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains many High and Wonderful My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, although the Word only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a <hi>Leavening</hi> or <hi>Working,</hi> and <hi>puffing up,</hi> or more properly the <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening</hi> or <hi>Reſolving</hi> of <hi>a thing in order for Maturation;</hi> however, under this Head is contained the principal Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the great Buſineſs both of Art and Nature; for as <hi>Philalathes,</hi> that Noble Engliſh Philoſopher, ſaith, <hi>it is the Wonder of the World;</hi> being that, by which Animals, Vegetables and Minerals receive their Concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49723:51"/>and without which it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that there ſhould be any Radical Union though of homoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Parts: For Nature firſt by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction prepares, and then by Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation ripens and maturates the ſame. Now as in Nature, ſo in Art for this tends beyond the Leaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Heightening or Fermenting Bread and Beer, for no true Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine can be prepared without the Knowledge of this Doctrine, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do we truly ſay, It is a Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, High and Myſterious one: But having touched at it in our <hi>Chymicus Rationalis,</hi> and more largly treated thereof in our <hi>Ignis Aſtralis Adeptorum,</hi> we ſhall only treat of that part of it here which ſhall be pertinent to our purpoſe, <hi>ſc.</hi> the Fermentation of Liquors; but we cannot omit of inſtancing this, That the Scriptures of Truth point forth the Verity of what we have here ſaid, witneſs Chriſt's Words, <hi>A little Leaven leavens the whole:</hi> And it is the Nature of Leaven to Ferment ſo long, as till it hath brought the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49723:52"/>whole Lump into its own Kind: And ſeeing it is really thus, we ſhall a little conſider by what Power this acts.</p>
            <p>The Power by which it acts and is acted upon is three-fold; the firſt and moſt principal is the <hi>Aireal Life,</hi> as it begins to find it ſelf oppoſed by contrary Particles, which doth, as it were, expand it ſelf for its own Defence, in oppoſition to its contrary. The ſecond is the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Warmth of Sulphur,</hi> which, as we may truly ſay, is the Garment and Defence of the ſaid <hi>Spirit,</hi> whereof if there be Quantity enough to ſupply its Action, then doth it never leave operating until it hath accompliſhed the deſired End, which is a full manifeſtation of the Light, Flowery, and Froathy Part of the Principles, the majority whereof is <hi>Sulphur,</hi> which lay diffuſed in the Liquor and hindered the Maturity thereof; yet being clivated and conjoyned, the Acid Fire therein contained hath Power to perform
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49723:52"/>the like Action, even <hi>ad Infinitum: Acid,</hi> we ſay, becauſe as 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Leaven and Barm ſoon four, and it is from that, as we well know, that the very Root of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation proceeds; for it is that which hath a contrary Action to the <hi>Vinor Alkalizated Spirits,</hi> in which Action it aſſembles together the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritous and Homogeneous Juices, making them yet more Spiritual; alſo precipitates the more groſs and corporal Parts thereof, with the which if a Liquor be overcharged, the Spiritual and Homogeneous Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities thereof will ſoon be eat out, either by ſome freſh Action, or other more inviſible way; which is the reaſon that Wines and other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors are ſo often wracked off from the Lees: And it is obſervable, That as Cyder begins to be upon the fret, the beſt way to preſerve the ſame, is immediately to wrack it off; but if you let the Fret get a height, it will be very difficult to preſerve the ſame. The third is the <hi>Moderate Warmth</hi> of <hi>the External
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49723:53"/>Heat</hi> and <hi>Air;</hi> for if that ſtands not in a Temperament ſomething Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathizing with the Internal Action, the ſame is in great Meaſure ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructured, as is evident by the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent working of Drink in Summer and Winter; for the Nature of Heat is to agitate and ſtir up, but that of Cold to Stagnatize and Coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; wherefore Fire and Heat muſt be uſed where Warmth is naturally deficient.</p>
            <p>Now from hence we may draw this Conſideration, <hi>ſc.</hi> That the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Heat is of the greateſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, becauſe that will work his way, except the external Quality be upon the extreme, as is evident in the difference between Strong Beer and Small; the one Working and Ripening it ſelf, when the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not; therefore we ſaid, That Sulphur was the Garment of the Spirit, whereby it is preſerv'd from the Extremes of Heat or Cold, by which its Activity is maintain'd; and the External Extremes muſt be
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49723:53"/>obſerved, in order to quicken the ſame Action; wherefore we ſet our <hi>Backs</hi> or <hi>Tuns</hi> colder in the Summer than in the Winter, and ſo vary accordingly, for the Heat of the Weather and Heat of the Wort would be two to one Odds, and Nature would always be ſullen, where ſhe is impoſed on; you muſt wait her Motions, or elſe take her by the Hand, and lead her gently, if you expect to have your Deſire anſwered; and bleſſed be the Lord our God, there is a Remnant ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with her mild and gentle Motion, and daily make it their Buſineſs to be more acquainted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; ſeeing it is ſhe only, as cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in the Will of the Creator, that muſt reward us with Health, Riches and long Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things being premiſed, we ſhall now come to touch at that, which may in great Meaſure help us with ſome Artificial Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when that, by which the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural is performed, is through an
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49723:54"/>imprudent Uſe and Negligence found ſhort and deficient.</p>
            <p>Now, in this Caſe you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider by what Qualities the Yeaſt acts, and ſo prepare a Ferment agreeable thereunto: The Old Country Wife helps herſelf much in this with Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Eggs; and ſome by that of Caſtle-ſoap; but we by a Union and Spiritual Action of the three Principles, in ſuch a way, that the Sulphur may be predominant; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſay, That if you have the true <hi>Eſſential Oyl of Barly</hi> ſo prepared, as juſt now hinted, you need not at any Time have any Deficiency or Shortneſs of Ferment, ſeeing it is durable, and a ſmall matter thereof will ſupply your Want: Alſo the true <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of <hi>Malt</hi> is not to be deſpiſed; nor the true <hi>Quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> of <hi>Wine:</hi> For that by theſe many excellent Secrets are perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but more eſpecially, and above all doth our <hi>Sal Panariſtus</hi> ſupply this Deficiency, in all and every part thereof, if it be but rightly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49723:54"/>uſed: For as the Famous <hi>Radolphus Glauber</hi> ſays concerning his <hi>Sal Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis</hi> or <hi>fixed Nitre, That if the ſame be with Flower throughly moyſtened with Warm Water, and ſet in a Warm Place, then, by its own proper Power and Vertue it begins to Ferment, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialty if ſome freſh Hops be put to the Water, by which alſo other Things are promoted to Fermentation: This ſerves not only for Yeast for Bakers, but Brewers may alſo thereby help them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for by it Wort may be excited into Fermentation;</hi> and the more high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our <hi>Sal Panariſtos</hi> is exalted and purified, the better both it perform this Operation, as being more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the Spiritual Action of Fermentation; therefore are we now labouring to produce it in ſuch Quantity, as may be ſufficient to give Demonſtration of its wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Vertue, to the moſt Ingenious Enquirers of Art. Many excellent and profitable Truths are in the Art of Fermentation, which being more largly treated of in our <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannean
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49723:55"/>Magazine,</hi> we omit it here; and come to the other Heads as follows.</p>
            <p>Now the Way, which Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhews to be the beſt, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Veſſels for the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Beer, is as follows; You muſt not at one Time ſcald them, and at another Time waſh them with cold Water, for that is the direct courſe to make your Beer get a Tangue of the Veſſel; for the Scalding of the Veſſel, as you call it, doth not ſo much waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Smell of the <hi>Tilts</hi> and <hi>Grounds,</hi> as it attracts and ſtirs up the Gummous, Raſomous and Ole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Part of the Wood unto the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Pores? and as that finds ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to operate with, it muſt be doing, then doth it give an hidden Ferment, and cauſe the Beer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Effects of that Tangue; for Nature is never one Moment idle, but will be doing, even when deprived of its Original Form, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49723:55"/>the Activity of the vivifying Spirit therein, as is evident in the Wood of Dead and Corrupted Trees, yea where the Life of its Vegetation is totally deſtroyed, for there by Fermentation and Putrefaction Worms are generated; which evidently makes good what we have ſaid. We alſo ſee, That after the Death of Human Kinds, yea while the Body is roting and Food for the Worms, that the Hair doth yet grow, whilſt it hath any Moyſture to ſuccor it, which although Excrementous, yet doth it vegetate; and ſo would every Form be doing ſomething, although it deſtroys a far more pleaſant one, as Beer is deſtroyed by the Tangue of the Cask.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Holland</hi> they ſeldom know the Effect of this evil Tangue, for that the Cask hath one Head taken out by the Brewers Servant or Cooper, and ſo brought to the River, and there with a Broom well waſhed, and every Chink thereof rubbed with a Bruſh, and then ſet an End, to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49723:56"/>let the Water run away; and ſome rub them with Hop leaves, that come out of the Wort, and ſo Rince them again; then being dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Air, and headed, they take a long Piece of Canvis, and diping it in Brimſtone they make Matches thereof, and with a few <hi>Coriander Seeds</hi> they ſet Fire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and opening the Bung they let the Match burn in the Veſſel, keeping in as much as they can of the Sulphurous Fume by laying the Bung lightly on, and when the Match is burned they ſtop all cloſe for a little Time; then being open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and coming to the Air, you find your Cask as ſweet as a Violet, for the Acid and Sulphurous Spirits have carried off all the Corruptive and Volatile Particles, and bound and conſtringed the more Solid and Sulphurous ones; Sulphurous, I ſay, becauſe the Wood burns like a Candle by reaſon of its Oyly Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for Sulphur is the Fiery Fuel of Wood and Coals, as Oyl is of a Lamp, for the Wet Mercurial,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49723:56"/>Saline Properties extinguiſh Fire, as is evident in the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Extreme Wet Wood and Dry. This plain Poſition brings me to conſider, By what Power and Action Trees ſubſiſt, living in the Winter, when they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their Flouriſhing Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. There be Various Opinions concerning this Point: It is the general Vogue, <hi>That the Sap and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Vertue of the Tree doth, as the Cold Approaches, fall down and retreat into the Root; and at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the Sun in the Spring, clivate itſelf again, to repleniſh the Tree in all and every part thereof:</hi> But <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peper,</hi> being a Man of a ſharp Wit, thought he had fully comprehended this things, and ſo went about the Confutation of this Opinion, by his endeavouring to ſhew, <hi>That the Cold conſtringed and bound the Sap in every part of the Tree alike in the Winter;</hi> ſaying, <hi>It returned not the the Root, but called them Sap-mongers, who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the ſame.</hi> Now our Moddler, having received from him this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49723:57"/>ſeems to impoſe a new Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thereon, and yet defines not the ſame, ſo as to give Satisfaction to ſuch as daily enquire into the great Buſineſs and Action of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>For Nature hath a wonderful and moſt myſterious way of working, ſhe performs her Actions by Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilizations and Fixations or by a rarifying Circulation and Conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, whence Maturation and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; theſe being carryed on and aided both by the External and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Powers, as was before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in that of Fermentation: So then we muſt conſider by what Power ſhe externally Rarifies, and by what Power ſhe condenſes, for as it is the Nature of the External Mercurial <hi>Gaſs</hi> to Bind and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringe the Pores of Trees, Plants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo is it of the External Heat, to mollifie and open the ſame, that ſo the Internal Heat may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in its rarifying Sublimation, which works oppoſite Effects to that of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49723:57"/>the former; for as the Internal, Mild and Mercurial Spirit doth pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate and open, ſo doth the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Warmth of Sulphur congeal and ripen. Now ſeeing theſe are neceſſary to be touched at in all and every part thereof, in order to clear this Doctrine, we ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as follows: Firſt, in touching at the Office of the Sun and Moon External, and then of thoſe Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, which are the four principal Powers of Nature, whereby ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhes her End.</p>
            <p>As to the External Sun and Moon, the one by the benignant Rays and vital Warmth of his Approach heats and illuminates that which the other by her Lunar Beams hath frigified and conſtringed: We ſhall firſt touch at the latter, and ſo begin at the Winter. For as the Sun declines his Vigour in any Latitude, ſhe is the more impowered there to ſhew her Activity; for in the Winter Cold and Diſmal, Hoary and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, Dumpiſh and Mournful are
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49723:58"/>the Earth and Products thereof to behold; for not only the Pores of its Superficies, but alſo of Trees, Plants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are bound up and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringed with Cold, which is yet more and more, as that increaſes; then doth not only the <hi>Central Sun</hi> and <hi>Archeius,</hi> but alſo the Central and Vital Life of Beings contract their warming Sulphurs and oleous Fuel, in order to preſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the terrifying Powers of Cold; nay they ſet Centinals to keep them off from approaching their Tents, that ſo none may paſs but what know the Word, for all things ſeek ſelf-Preſervation: By this means the Centre of the Earth and Internal Powers of other things are warmer in the Winter than in the Summer, as thoſe Springs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, even to a Vapour; and in this warmth an increaſe of Radical Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture is made, from whence Putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and Condenſation in order for Vegetation, which is performed,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49723:58"/>as the Heat of the Sun approaches, ſo as to open the Pores of the Earth, Trees and Vegetables, reſtoring their Barren and half-decayed Natures to their priſtine Activity: Then doth the Central Fire again expand it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſhewing its Activity in Subli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Vapors, in which the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Spirit is attracted, and again rarified into that Oyly and Vital Fuel, which cauſes the increaſe of Trees, Graſs and Flowers, being attracted in at the Roots thereof, aſcending to the Body, Branches, Buds, Flowers and Fruit, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes ſo long in Strength, as the external Heat hath Power to Act, or till the Form hath given an end to its determinating Power, for one Fire attracts another, ſo doth the Celeſtial Sun the Vapor of the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral one in this Action; ſo ſubtle is Nature as to attract and lay up Stores for her future Preſervation: Hence it is, that the ſorming Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur congeals and maturates what is ſufficient for the producing of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49723:59"/>Fruits; for theſe, ſtanding in a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> between the Central and Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial, have the Beneſit of both, we mean, the ſpecificating Power, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to Seed, in order for Concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Formation, for the Celeſtial Sun only attracts the Spiritual Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por, which is the Vehicle for the conveying the nouriſhing Fuel to the different Forms; which Vapor doth, as it were, follow the Sun, as he paſſes through diverſities of Climates, and hath his Active Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er there, according to his prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence in the Seaſon and Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Motion, which is the Reaſon why Vegetation is at one Time here, another Time there, ſometimes in the Northern, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Southern part of the World; for the great God hath univerſally diſpenſed his bounteous Gifts to the whole Creation, it all being the Work of his Hands; and therefore in deſcribing the Nature of Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, we muſt have ſome Regard to the whole, otherwiſe it may be
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49723:59"/>performed but defectively: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſay, That this Vapor not improperly called the <hi>Mercury of Life,</hi> ſeing that therein Centrals and Celeſtials are united, without any Determination of Form, paſſes here and there in Search of the ſame, ſympathizing with the Heavenly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, even round the whole Globe of the Earth, in order to cauſe Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getation; the which is performed in every Place, ſo long as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Heat hath Predominancy, but as that declines, ſo comes on the Lunar Effects, in producing the Winter: And this is the Office of the Celeſtial Sun and Moon, and the Reaſon of Winter and Summer in all Places.</p>
            <p>Now as to the Internal, we a little before ſaid, That the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of theſe are ſomething dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to the former, by their ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Oppoſite, yet harmonious Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; for as the External Heat en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes and dilates the Pores of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49723:60"/>Trees, Plants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo at the ſame Time doth the Internal Cold, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed, Mercurial Spirits aſcend, penetrating all Things, that have a Root in Nature, in Order to cauſe their Vegetation, which is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by the more Sulphurous Warmth, following the ſame as Fire doth Smoak, theſe being the Fuel and nouriſhing Vertue of the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Powers; yet is it but the light and undeterminated Form, which as it nouriſhes the Seminal Vertue of the Tree or Plant is converted into its Subſtance, and then receives the Determination of Form, from the forming Power Originally given by the great Creator unto the Seminal Vertue therein contained; for that every thing was to increaſe and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply by means of a Seed therein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed; and at the very ſame Time, that the External Heat is buſie to dilate, the internal Warmth is ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, and as a Male, acts in the Congelation of that Moiſture, in order that it may get a more Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49723:60"/>Nature for Increaſe; alſo for Strength and future Nouriſhment to the real Subſtance thereof; that ſo it may defend it ſelf againſt the extreme of Cold.</p>
            <p>Hence we conceive, That while the internal Spirits are aſcending by Sublimation, which continues ſo long as the External Heat aſſiſts the ſame, all this while is Nature build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing herſelf a Neſt, and Antlike, providing her Food againſt Winter; one Part ſhe converts into Bark, another into Wood and Subſtance, another into Fruit and Seed, by which means the ſubtilized Spirit that aſcends, is ſo exhauſted in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to preſerve the Specie, that it hath none to ſpare for a deſcention, and as little for a Congelation into Sap; for the Sublimation of the Vapor ceaſes and the Bottle is then ſtoped, and had it not an internal Nouriſhing Seminal Balſamick Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, to preſerve its Strength, it were impoſſible for it to ſubſiſt till another Supply, Succour, or new
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49723:61"/>Sublimation of Vapor; and had not the Internal Heat dryed up and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porified the ſaid Moiſture, 'twere impoſſible that the ſubſiſting Strength ſhould be ſo upheld in Nature as it is even in the Deſiciency of the Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Rays of the Vivifying and Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Sun; but it is very evident and agreeable to the Laws of Nature, that Drineſs and internal Warmth ſhould concentrate, ſo as to give Durability, in that thoſe, which are Moiſt, Green, Young and Tender in the Winter, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily Dye and Wither; nay moſt Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables creep their Heads into the Earth for Warmth, as the Stork ſlies to another Climate: Hence it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, That the Sap is not congealed in the Nature of Sap, which is the Chylous Juice of the firſt Action; but as the Chyle of Man's Body is by degrees of Concoction, Fermentation, Digeſtion and Exaltation converted into the Subſtance of Blood and Nervous Juices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo is this into a more Corporal Balſam, nay even as was ſaid before, into the real Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Tree itſelf: Hence it
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49723:61"/>is, and for want of a freſh Supply of Vapor, (by the Radical Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Union of both which the Sap is again produced) that the whole Tree in all its parts is abundantly more dry in the Winter than in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and were the Sap congealed in the Tree, as ſome ſuppoſe, then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly would it contain Moiſture ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſuccour and nouriſh itſelf another Year for Vegetation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Supply, which Experience poſitively contradicts: For if in the ſpring the Vapor is obſtructed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to ſhew its nouriſhing Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, the being thereof ſo deprived becomes as the off ſpring of the Dead, for it hath been for this Seaſon only preſerved by the Magnetick Power of the <hi>Polar Axis,</hi> and by having Root in the Earth, where the Internal Warmth is, and from the Strength obtained in the Seaſon from the matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating Sulphur, Central Fire or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Heat, which, as is all-a long ſaid, gives Strength and Maturity to Beings for the Winter-Seaſon, which is compared to the Hoary Head of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49723:62"/>Old Age, wherein the youth ful Strength and Vigour is ſpent; therefore Trees yearly renovate, as hath been touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, for it is manifeſt that Trees in their Vegetative Seaſon are full of Sap, that they will ſearce or not at all burn; whenas they will in that of the contrary freely do it; and though Moiſture ſometimes proceeds from dryer Wood burned, yet is not that ſo much the Sap, as the Principles bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Violence of Fire, and a Vineager moſtly proceeding from the Sulphurous Quality, ſeeing the ſame may artificially be produced from the drieſt of Coals: Thus have you the general Office of the Celeſtial Sun and Moon, as alſo of the Terreſtrial and Central in producing and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Vegetative Power and Strength in Trees, Plants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby it is plain that the External Heat opens, and the external Cold congeals, <hi>&amp; vice verſa,</hi> that the Internal Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial Spirit Diſſolves, but the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sulphurous one coagulates; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it, that in our Opinion it is moſt proper to uſe Cold Water, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49723:62"/>cauſe that External Heat is apt to ſtir up the Internal one, and if that have not ſome Artificial Check, it will preſently work ſome evil effect; therefore do we adviſe, That the Fumes of <hi>Sulphur,</hi> as alſo the <hi>Diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Waſh,</hi> be uſed to ſweeten, where theſe Rules have been neglected; becauſe it is full of that Gum, which aſſatiates the other's Thirſt.</p>
            <p>Now as to tunning, there be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious manners uſed by moſt or all Brewers, one being of Opinion, That it is beſt tunned, as it curles or begins to come; another lets it be yet more ripe; but we ſay it is beſt to Cleanſe and Tun juſt as the Beer comes to a due Ferment, and gets a good Head; for then it hath the moſt Strength to cleanſe itſelf in the Cask: And you may obſerve, That what works over muſt be again ſupplyed with Freſh Peer of the ſame Brewing; the Workings may be added to your Small-Beer, or elſe to your Barm, and let the clear run through a large <hi>Hyppocrates Sleeve</hi> or
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49723:63"/>Flannel Bag, made in Form of a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramide, the Point being downwards, with a Hoop at the Top, hanging the ſame over a Tub; and if you have great Quantities of Cleanſings, you may in a large Brewing get a Barrel of Beer.</p>
            <p>Now things being thus ordered in Fermentation, Cleanſing the Veſſels and Tunning, it may be a great means for the preſerving of the Beer: But however, <hi>Fixed Niter</hi> is as a ſole Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, for it keeps the Beer from any Fret or Unnatural Ferment; nay it will reſtore Decayed Beer unto its priſtine Vigour, as will be ſeen in the next Chapter; therefore do we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this and proceed to that.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:49723:63"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> In which we ſhall treat of Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Beer, and reſtoring ſuch as is Sour and Decayed, ſo as to render it drinkable.</head>
            <p>THe ways of clearing of Beer are many and various; but the beſt thing to make it very Fine is <hi>Fixed Niter,</hi> as alſo the <hi>Quinteſſence of Malt,</hi> and of <hi>Wine;</hi> for theſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spiritual, render it alſo Clear, Thin and Spiritual, and preſerve it; <hi>Whites of Eggs</hi> being made into Balls with a little <hi>Flower</hi> and caſt into the Beer, do wonderfully Cleanſe, Feed and preſerve the ſame, eſpecially if. you add a little <hi>Izing-Glaſs</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. The Experience of the <hi>Oyl of Barley</hi> eſſentially made gives wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Satisfaction in the Feeding and Nouriſhing of Beer, ſeeing that, as all other things, requires nouriſhment
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49723:64"/>to preſerve its Being. The <hi>Quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Barley</hi> doth alſo wenderfully Nouriſh and Strengthen Beer. It is alſo Cleared and Strengthened, even to ſuch a degree, as that it may be called <hi>Beer Royal;</hi> which is by add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into it in Fermentation ſome Burning Spirit, which doth not only clear the Beer, but alſo add Strength and Durability thereunto, making it fit for Tranſportation to any Part of the World, far beyond that of <hi>Double Beer,</hi> for the ſame Reaſon as is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in our <hi>Britannean Magazine</hi> for <hi>Vinum Fortificatum</hi> or <hi>Syder Royal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Beer thus ordered ſeldom or never ſours for many Years, but if it ſhould not be ſo ordered but come to ſour, we muſt look for a Remedy to recover the ſame; and this may be eprformed by ſome <hi>Alkalizated</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which imbibes the Acidity by Precipitation, and frees the Liquor therefrom: Of this Nature is the Salt made from the Aſhes of Barley Straw, being put in the Veſſell and wel ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Glamber commends three or four
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49723:64"/>Handfuls of Beech-Aſhes, being throws into the Veſſel after the ſame manner,</hi> or if be not too very ſour, a little put in a Bag, without ſtirring performs the ſame. <hi>Chalk</hi> being put into ſour. Beer immediately renders it drinkable. Alſo Calcined <hi>Oyſter-Shells,</hi> or <hi>Calx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive, Egg-Shells burned, Tortoiſe-Shels, Sea-Shells, Crabs-Eyes, Alkalized Coral,</hi> for that they imbibe and attract the Sharpneſs, and turn it into Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Which alſo may in great Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be performed by a Handful of Wheat being thrown into the Veſſel; for this Sharpneſs proceeds from the want of Strength and Spirits, or elſe from thoſe wnating ſomething to feed on: And therefore do we commend the true <hi>Alkalized Quinteſſence</hi> of <hi>Malt,</hi> not only for returning Sour Beer Sweet, but alſo for the Feeding and Nouriſhing ſuch, as is Sound, for its future Preſervation. <hi>Glauber</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully commends his <hi>Sal Mirabilis,</hi> and <hi>Fixed Niter, to be put in a Linnen Bag, and hung in the Top of the Cask, ſo as to reach unto the Liquor, not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r rendring Sour Beer Drinkable, but
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49723:65"/>alſo for Preſerving and Strengthening the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having given you the Grounds and Reaſon, whence Fermentation proceeds, and how the ſame may be reaſonably exalted or prevented; and how Beer may be preſerved from Souring, as alſo how meaſurably to recover the ſame, when ſo, by ſuch Rules and Examples, as may enable you to preſcribe others, and make your Variations as need requires, we think it ſufficient; and therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to other Requiſites.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:49723:65"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> In which we treat concerning the making of ſeveral Phyſical Drinks, together with their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: Shewing the right way of Bottleing Beer.</head>
            <p>AS to the Ways of making Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Drinks, they are vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; ſome being made from Herbs, others by the Spirits thereof exalted, others by their Eſſential Salts and their Eſſences exalted, which indeed is the moſt ſuperior Way; but ſeeing that every Brewer and good Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife cannot obtain theſe, we ſhall preſcribe ſuch, as be of more eaſie Preparation.</p>
            <p>We ſee that Beer made from <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, Cedar, Saſſafrax, Wormwood, Scurveygraſs, Elder, Mint, Balm,</hi> &amp;c. are highly eſteemed, eſpecially <hi>Purle</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:49723:66"/>and <hi>Scurvygraſs,</hi> here in <hi>England:</hi> But here is one thing which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not omit, which is this, they take the Herbs at any Seaſon, with the Groſs and more Vertuous part together; and put theſe into Low, Weak, Sick, Defective or Prick'd Beers, and ſo the Taſt of the Herb overpowering the ſame, they think it ſufficient, the Pallats of the Drinkers being pleaſed, not minding whether they anſwer the End deſired, <hi>ſc.</hi> the contributing ſomething to the Health of their Drinkers, which they cannot thus do, ſeeing they want that Internal Sanity themſelves, which ſhould perform the ſame. Now ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is not only this, but much more, which might be ſaid of the like Nature, we ſhall recommend three things to the Conſideration of every Honeſt Brewer, whereby this Defect may in great Meaſure be Repaired and Supplyed: The firſt is, if you deſign to make any ſort of Phyſical Beer, let your Wort have a Sound Body, well wrought, and ſettle three Days, and while it hath yet a more
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49723:66"/>Inviſible and Secret Fermentation. Secondly, that you only add in the Tops and choice Parts of ſuch Herbs as are deſign'd for the ſame. And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That thoſe Herbs lie not ſo long therein, as that their Spiritual Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities may be ſo much exhauſted, that their Terrene ones by the Beer or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor ſhould be extracted; therefore they ought to be well pounded and macerated, and in a ſmall Bag put into the Cask, that ſo after their due Time, which may be at the moſt twenty Days, they may be taken out again. Theſe being obſerved, you may make excellent Beer or Drinks, fully anſwering the End of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. Alſo inſtead of ſuch Herbs as are naturally juicy, you may add in the Juice thereof; if <hi>Elder,</hi> let it be about two Gallons to a Barrel of Strong Beer; but if the Juices are S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iptick, Eitter or Aſtringent, then will a ſmaller Quantity ſerve. You may alſo have moſt excellent Phyſical Ales, by adding the Spirits of the Concreats truly prepared, about thirty or forty Drops, more or leſs,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49723:67"/>according to their Strength, into a Glaſs of Beer: The True <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Salt</hi> is an excellent Preſerver unto Human Bodies, being taken ten or twelve Drops after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>It cures the Scurvey, reſiſts Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifaction,</hi> &amp;c. Alſo eight or ten Drops hereof being dropped into a Quart of New Beer, makes it immediately taſt St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, and renders it drinkable. But above all doth our <hi>Spiritus Odon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas</hi> perform this, as you may ſee at large in the <hi>Britannean Magazine of Wines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if you have a mind to have any other Variations, in making di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Phyſical Ales, then proceed thus; Make a Syrrup of the Herb, and put two or three Spoonfuls thereof into the Ale or Beer in Bottleing, and a Spoonful or two of the Eſſence, whether it be <hi>Oranges, Lemons,</hi> or <hi>Scurvygraſs, Cypreſs, Wormwood, Mint, Balm,</hi> or the like: And if you practiſe this, your Experience will prompt you beyond Words.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:49723:67"/>
               <head>A Compound Phyſical Ale, good againſt the Scurvy, Dropſy, and other Diſeaſes.</head>
               <p>OF Scurvy graſs one Peck,<note place="margin">℞.</note> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Creſces twelve Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, Brooklime ſix handfuls, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Rhubard ſix ounces, Horſe Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh four ounces, Anniſeeds and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raway Seeds of each one ounce, Sweet Fennel one ounce, Sena one ounce, Polipody of the Oak four ounces, Raiſins ſtoned and Lent Figs, of each eight ounces, New Ale five gallons; make it <hi>S. A.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good way for the Bottling Beer.</head>
               <p>IN the firſt Place take a little clear Water, or elſe ſuch as is truly impregnated with the Eſſence of any Herb, and to every Quart thereof add half a pound of <hi>Mevis Sugar,</hi> and having very gently boyled and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49723:68"/>ſcumed the ſame, adding thereunto a few <hi>Cloves,</hi> let it cool, fit to put Barm thereto; and being brought to work, ſcum off the ſame again, and while it is in a ſmiling condition put three ſpoonfuls thereof to each Bottle, and then filling up the ſame, cork faſt down. A ſew <hi>Chriſtals</hi> of <hi>Tartar</hi> alſo do well in Bottling Beer, adding a few Drops of the <hi>Eſſence of Barly, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Wine,</hi> or ſome other <hi>Eſſential Spirits.</hi> Accept of this (Courteous Reader) until Opportunity ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit us to oblige you with things of a more Sublime Nature.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:49723:68"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>IN this Treatiſe, having ſpoke of Waters in general, laying down Rules ſufficient to inform any reaſonable Man of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Preparation, yet I think it may not be amiſs to add a few Words as a Review of the whole, that is, how Waters are altered by the Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Qualities, as well as by the Natural ones, and from ſuch things that ſuperficially impregnate the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with ſomething contrary to its internal Texture, that is, it purges itſelf therefrom once, peradventure, in a Natural Day by its being ponder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, it joyns with the earthy Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Water, and ſo precipitates and waſhes away; but however if
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49723:69"/>it is conſtantly impregnated with ſuch Heterogeneities, It much alters the Purity of the Water, and makes the Time very uncertain: When we take it purged, or when its Body is filled with the ſaid Impurity, and ſo one and the ſame Water ſhall vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly alter in the manner of Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Fermentation, being taken at various Times. You have an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this in <hi>Thames</hi> water, a pure and ſine River, originally proceeding from a Spring, being fed by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux of many ſmall Rivulents, and ſo increaſed to ſuch a magnitude, as it is ſo navigable, that it challenges many of the <hi>European</hi> Rivers apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining unto the Metropolitan Cities; but however it hath theſe Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as others have alſo, for being near ſo great a City, it receives the Common Shores, and from its adjacent Banks various Excrementious Things, as Dung, Urin, Fiſh-Bones, Diers-Liquor, Soap-boylers Drugs, the Butchers Corruptions, and many other Sulphurous, Stinking and Slimy Things, which wonderfully alter the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49723:69"/>Water, ſo that ſometimes, eſpecially if taken in the Time, when it is not purged, the Wort will not bear boyling, but becomes thick, and will not kindly Ferment, and ſo drinks flubby, unpleaſant, and ſhews the like Effects, for it will ſoon Sour and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt; ſo that many, who uſe the <hi>Thames</hi> Water, are afraid to boyl their Liquor or Wort ſufficient, becauſe it will grow thick, and this by them is generally obſerved, but the reaſon thereof not conceived: For other Times the Water being taken, when it hath purged itſelf, it may be boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſame Succeſs as other Waters, and the Beer or Ale will be very Clear and Durable, drinking Brisk and Pleaſant: The wonderful Difference of Beer and Ale, brewed from the <hi>Thames</hi> Water, is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to many of the Curious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers, neither is the Reaſon thereof ſo obſcure, but that it may be eaſily comprehended; ſeeing Water is the general Menſtruum, taking in the impure as well as the purer Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, even after it is in a meaſure
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49723:70"/>aſſatiated with the Elixeration of the Malt; for how many different Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors may be impregnated in the Wort, from whence the various or different Reliſhes to Beer or Ale pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds: For if we add but a few Coriander-Seeds, gently infuſed in a ſmall quantity of Wort, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward wrought in the whole, it will make it drink like Chinay-Ale; and ſo if you add an Ounce of the Powder of Orrice into a Quart of new Drink, gently infuſed, and then add that to a Barrel, it gives it the Reliſh of the Raſtberry, adding ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue thereunto; for this Reaſon do we adviſe you to add ſix or eight Ounces of Ginger, and as much Orrice to an Hogſhed of Strong Wormwood; and then you will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich it ſo, as two or three Spoonfuls will be ſufficient for a Quart of clear Drink, having Vertues alſo equal with the ſmalneſs of its Doſe. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Black-cherries, Elder-berries, Rasberries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being added, make excellent and vertuous Drinks; nay how many Phyſical Ales may be made
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49723:70"/>by Simple and Compound Infuſions; but ſeeing this is ſo obvious to all, that impregnation of different Idea's gives a different Alteration of Vertue, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they proceed from a pure Root, but the contrary if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from an impure one, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by daily Experience.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49723:71"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p n="1">I. DR. <hi>Y. worth</hi>'s <hi>Pilula Anodyna Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificata &amp; Cathartica,</hi> or the Friendly Balſamick Pill. The Doſe is one Pill, Price one Shill. <hi>per</hi> Box.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Species Noſtra Mineralis,</hi> or the Spagyrical Triumphant Powder; the Paper containing 3 Doſes, Price one Shilling Six Pence.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Cordonum Regale Lenitum,</hi> or the Royal Purging Cordial; the Doſe is from one to three Spoonfuls, half Pint Bottle Price two Shillings and ſix Pence.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that deſire to be furniſhed with theſe, or any of them, either Wholeſale or Retail, may apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Author, at the <hi>Blue Ball</hi> and <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>S. Paul's Shadwel:</hi> Or to <hi>Jo. Spire,</hi> Phyſician, at the <hi>two Blew twiſted Poſts</hi> in <hi>Fair-Street,</hi> on <hi>Horſly-Down.</hi> or to <hi>Jo. Taylor,</hi> Bookſeller, at the <hi>Ship</hi> in <hi>S. Paul's Church-Yard:</hi> Or to Mr. <hi>Jo. Baker,</hi> Perriwig-maker, at the <hi>Wool-pack</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:49723:71"/>
               <head>Books Printed for <hi>Samuel Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> at the <hi>Swan</hi> in <hi>S. Paul's Church-Yard.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Engliſh Grammar,</hi> ſetting forth the Grounds of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Tongue;</hi> and particularly its Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius in making Compounds and Deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatives, with many other Uſeful and Curious Obſervations: Wherein are alſo Explained the uſual Abbreviati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the ſeveral Hands uſed in Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Characters in Printing, the Variety of Styles, the Art of true Pointing, and the way to underſtand Books: With a Prefatory Diiſcourſe about the Original and Excellency of the Engliſh Tongue; And at the end an Alphabetick Collection of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſyllables, being a Treatiſe of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thography for Writers, and of Rhimes for Poets. A Neceſſary Work in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral for all Perſons deſirous to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Ground and Genius of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and very proper to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Young Men for the <hi>Latin Tongue.</hi> By <hi>Guy Miege,</hi> Gent.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49723:72"/>
               <p>God's Revenge againſt Murther and Adultery, expreſſed in Thirty ſeveral Tragical Hiſtories: Wherein are live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delinated the various Stratagems, ſubtle Practices and deluding Oratory uſed by our Modern Galants, in order to the ſeducing young Ladies to their unlawful Pleaſures. To which are annexed the Triumps of Friendſhip and Chaſtity, in ſome Heroical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and Delightful Hiſtories. The whole illuſtrated with about fifty Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Epiſtles, relating to Love and Gallantry. By <hi>Thomas Wright,</hi> M. A. of <hi>S. Peter's College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Compleat Hiſtory of the Late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, from the firſt Riſe of it to this preſent Time; in Three Parts.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49723:72"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
